WELCOME TO THE JANUARY 6TH, 2026 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL. THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER NOT PRESENT SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN PRESENT MANDEL MEN PRESENT SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR SARDAR SAUTER
PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL PRESENT SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR WANG WONG
PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT YOU HAVE A QUORUM.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL
HOMELAND OF THE ROMITA SALONI WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL
INHABITANTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA.
AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE
WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE RAW MATERIALS WE HAVE NEVER CEDED
LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL TERRITORY.
AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING
ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOMELAND. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE
RAMAKRISHNA ALONI COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR
SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE? I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG
OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND TO THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH
IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD, INDIVISIBLE, WITH LIBERTY
AND JUSTICE FOR ALL. >> ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD I
WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT S.F. GOV TV TODAY THAT IS
ESPECIALLY KALEENA MENDOZA. THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR
MEETINGS AND MAKE THE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE
PUBLIC ONLINE. MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY
COMMUNICATIONS? >> YES, MR. PRESIDENT.
WE ARE IN RECEIPT OF A MEMO FROM SUPERVISOR JACKIE FIELDER
REQUESTING TO BE EXCUSED FROM TODAY'S MEETING.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COULD I HAVE A MOTION TO
EXCUSED SUPERVISOR FIELDER MADE BY CHEN AND SECONDED BY DORSEY
AND COLLEAGUES. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT
WITHOUT OBJECTION. THE MOTION PASSES.
AND MADAM CLERK, WAS THAT IT FOR COMMUNICATIONS.
>> TO FINISH QUICKLY THE BOARD WELCOMES YOUR ATTENDANCE IN THE
CHAMBER FOR OUR FIRST MEETING OF THE LEGISLATIVE SESSION.
WHEN YOU'RE NOT ABLE TO BE HERE THE PROCEEDING IS AIRING LIVE
ON AS OF JEHOVAH TV'S CHANNEL 26 WHERE YOU CAN VIEW THE
LIVESTREAM AT W W W DOT S.F. GEO VTV DOT ORG.
YOU CAN SEND YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT IN WRITING IF YOU SEND
AN EMAIL TO B O S AT S F GOV DAWG.
OR IF YOU'RE USING THE POSTAL SERVICE ADDRESS THE ENVELOPE TO
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON B GOOD PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244
IN SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA 94102.
AND LASTLY, IF YOU NEED TO MAKE A REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION FOR
A FUTURE MEETING UNDER THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT
OR IF YOU NEED TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE, PLEASE
CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS DAYS
IN ADVANCE BY CALLING 41555545184.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
LET'S GO TO APPROVAL OF OUR MEETING MINUTES.
>> YES. APPROVAL OF THE NOVEMBER 4TH
2025 BOARD MEETING MINUTES. CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE
THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED MOVED BY WALTON AND SECONDED BY CHAN.
MADAM CLERK WE PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR EYES SUPERVISOR SADR
SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN
EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYE AND SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN EYE
MANDALAY MEN EYE THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT AS PRESENTED
MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR CONSENT AGENDA ITEMS ONE
THROUGH THREE YES ITEMS ONE THROUGH THREE ARE ON CONSENT
THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED TO BE ROUTINE IF A MEMBER OBJECTS
AN ITEM MAY BE REMOVED AND CONSIDERED SEPARATELY.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS ONE THROUGH THREE
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR EYES SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYE SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYE AND SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
MENDELSON I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THESE
ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR
REGULAR AGENDA NEW BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEM FOUR ITEM
FOUR. >> THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO
AMEND THE PLANNING CODE TO DEFINE A FAMILY AS A HOUSEHOLD
TO ELIMINATE NUMERIC LIMITS ON UNRELATED FAMILY MEMBERS
AND REQUIREMENTS THAT FAMILY MEMBERS SHARE MEALS, CLASSIFY
RESIDENTIAL CARE FACILITIES THAT SERVE SIX OR FEWER PERSONS
AS RESIDENTIAL USES TO INCLUDE CERTAIN GROUPS OF SIX OR FEWER
PEOPLE AND ASSOCIATED OPERATORS AS A HOUSEHOLD.
TO CLARIFY THE ZONING ADMINISTRATORS ENFORCEMENT
AUTHORITY TO ADMINISTRATIVELY SUBPOENA DOCUMENTS AND TO
AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE
FINDINGS. >> LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM FIVE.
>> ITEM FIVE THIS RESOLUTION DETERMINES THAT THE PERSON TO
PERSON PREMISE TO PREMISE TRANSFER OF A TYPE 21 OFF SALE
GENERAL BEER WINE AND DISTILLED SPIRITS LIQUOR LICENSE TO REAL
MART LLC DOING BUSINESS AS UNIT MART LOCATED AT 12 ZERO ONE
HOWARD STREET WILL NOT SERVE THE PUBLIC CONVENIENCE OR
NECESSITY OF THE CITY AND TO REQUEST THAT THE WELL TO
REQUEST THAT THE DEPARTMENT OF ALCOHOLIC AND BEVERAGE CONTROL
DENY THE ISSUANCE OF THE LICENSE AND WE CAN TAKE THIS
ONE SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
SIX AND SEVEN TOGETHER ITEM SIX AND 7 OR 2 RESOLUTIONS THAT
DETERMINE THAT TWO LIQUOR LICENSES WILL SERVE THE PUBLIC
CONVENIENCE OR NECESSITY OF THE CITY.
ITEM SIX DETERMINES THAT THE PERSON TO PERSON PREMISE TO
PREMISE TRANSFER OF A TYPE 48 ON SALE GENERAL PUBLIC PREMISES
BEER WINE AND DISTILLED SPIRITS LIQUOR LICENSE TO BIG SKY LLC
DOING BUSINESS AS CLUB 895 LOCATED AT 895 O'FARRELL STREET
AND I AM SEVEN WHICH DETERMINES THAT THE PERSON TO PERSON
PREMISE TO PREMISE TRANSFER OF A TYPE 20 OFF SALE BEER
AND WINE LIQUOR LICENSE TO CALDERA LLC DOING BUSINESS AS
CALDERA LOCATED AT 2149 UNION STREET THAT BOTH WILL SERVE THE
PUBLIC CONVENIENCE OR NECESSITY OF THE CITY AND TO REQUEST THAT
THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF ALCOHOLIC BEVERAGE CONTROL
IMPOSE CONDITIONS ON THE ISSUANCE OF EACH LICENSE
AND AGAIN SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. >> MADAME CLERK LET'S GO TO A
ROLL CALL UP. >> WHOOPS.
SORRY SKIP THAT RATHER CALL PLEASE CALL ITEM EIGHT.
ITEM EIGHT THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO ACCEPT THE BIANNUAL
SURVEILLANCE REPORT UNDER THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE SECTION 19
BE A POINT SIX FOR THE JUVENILE PROBATION DEPARTMENT AND THIS
ONE WE CAN DO SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> AND NOW LET'S GO TO ROLL
CALL. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
FIRST UP TO INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS IS SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION ALONG WITH SUPERVISORS CHEN CHAN
FIELDER MANAGEMENT CHERYL WANG AND MAHMUD TO COMMEMORATE THE
ROH VERSUS WADE DECISION ON JANUARY 22ND, 1973 WHICH FOR
NEARLY 50 YEARS RECOGNIZED ABORTION AS A FUNDA MENTAL
CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHT AND AFFIRMED THE ABILITY OF
INDIVIDUALS TO MAKE PERSONAL HEALTH CARE DECISIONS FREE FROM
UNDUE GOVERNMENT INFLUENCE. WELL, THE ROH DECISION WAS
OVERTURNED BY THIS SUPREME COURT IN 2022 BY THE DOBBS
DECISION. ITS ANNIVERSARY REMAINS A
POWERFUL REMINDER OF THE ROLE GOVERNMENT PLAYS IN EITHER
PROTECTING OR UNDERMINING BODILY AUTONOMY, PRIVACY
AND HEALTH CARE ACCESS. >> THE CONSEQUENCES OF THE
DOBBS DECISION WERE PROFOUND AND IMMEDIATE IT ENABLING
STATES TO CRIMINALIZE SURVEIL, PENALIZED REPRODUCTIVE HEALTH
CARE CAUSING DISPROPORTIONATE HARM TO WOMEN, TO GIRLS, TO
NONBINARY PEOPLE PARTICULARLY THOSE WHO ARE LOW INCOME
MEDICALLY UNDERSERVED AND UNDERINSURED BLACK
INDIGENOUS LATINA PEOPLE OF COLOR IMMIGRANTS AND YOUNG
PEOPLE. SAN FRANCISCO HAS LONG SERVED
AS A NATIONAL LEADER IN PROTECTING REPRODUCTIVE
FREEDOM AND ADVANCING REPRODUCTIVE JUSTICE.
OUR STATE LAWS AND CONSTITUTION PROVIDE STRONG PROTECTIONS FOR
REPRODUCTIVE RIGHTS INCLUDING EXPLORE ASSET PRIVACY
GUARANTEES, ABORTION AND CONTRACEPTIVE ACCESS.
PROTECTIONS AGAINST HARASSMENT, OBSTRUCTION.
VIOLENCE AT REPRODUCTIVE HEALTH CARE FACILITIES.
>> ULTIMATELY THIS RESOLUTION MATTERS BECAUSE LOCAL
GOVERNMENTS ARE ON THE FRONT LINES.
>> AT A TIME WHEN NATIONAL ROLLBACKS TODAY WE SAW IT'S A
WAR AGAINST WOMEN AND CHILDREN IN OUR COUNTRY RIGHT NOW
CLEARLY AND PUBLICLY WE MUST SUPPORT REPRODUCTIVE FREEDOM,
FREEDOM, BODILY AUTONOMY, PRIVACY, REPRODUCTIVE JUSTICE.
IT REMAINS CORE VALUES OF OUR CITY AND WE WILL ACTUALLY ACT
ACTIVELY DEFEND THEM. >> SAN FRANCISCO ENACTED
ADDITIONAL SAFEGUARDS TO ENSURE SAFE, UNOBSTRUCTED ACCESS TO
CARE AND TO HOLD ACCOUNTABLE THOSE WHO INTERFERE WITH
PATIENTS OR PROVIDERS. >> THIS RESOLUTION REAFFIRMS
THE CITY'S COMMITMENT TO UPHOLDING THESE SAFEGUARDS.
REINFORCES COORDINATED PROTOCOLS WITH THE POLICE
DEPARTMENT, DISTRICT ATTORNEY DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH
AND OTHER AGENCIES TO ENSURE ACCOUNTABILITY FOR VIOLATION OF
CLINIC ACCESS AND SAFETY LAWS AND MAKES CLEAR THAT CITY
RESOURCES, PERSONNEL AND DATA WILL NOT BE USED TO ASSIST OUT
OF STATE INVESTIGATIONS OR LEGAL ACTIONS TARGETING
REPRODUCTIVE HEALTH CARE THAT IS LAWFUL IN CALIFORNIA AND IN
SAN FRANCISCO. IN CLOSING, I WANT TO THANK THE
DEPARTMENT OF THE STATUS OF WOMEN, ESPECIALLY OUR NEW
DIRECTOR, DR. DONATO AND HER STAFF.
THE COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN PLANNED PARENTHOOD, THE
HEALTH CARE PROVIDERS WORKING IN PARTNERSHIP WITH OUR
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH AND OUR CITY ATTORNEYS FOR
THEIR LEADERSHIP AND STEADFAST WORK DEFENDING REPRODUCTIVE
FREEDOM FOR WOMEN AND GIRLS IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR. SUPERVISOR SAUTER SMITH THANK
YOU. SUPERVISOR CHERYL COLLEAGUES,
I'D LIKE TO ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING IN MEMORY OF DIOSDADO
BONITO, A PIONEERING ON ENGINEER ENTREPRENEUR
AND PHILANTHROPIST WHOSE WORK AND INVENTIONS HELPED SHAPE THE
MODERN PERSONAL COMPUTER AND WHOSE GENEROSITY EXPANDED
OPPORTUNITY FOR GENERATIONS. >> KNOWN BY ALL HIS DATA, HE
PIONEERED KEY COMPUTER AND GRAPHICS CHIP TECHNOLOGIES
THAT MADE PERSONAL COMPUTERS MORE AFFORDABLE, POWERFUL
AND PROACTIVE FOR EVERYDAY USE. DATO BONITO PEACEFULLY PASSED
AWAY THIS PAST CHRISTMAS DAY IN PALO ALTO SURROUNDED BY
FAMILY AND FRIENDS. HE WAS BORN ON MAY 23RD, 1946
IN E GREGG, PHILIPPINES TO SALVADOR AND ROSITA BONA TOWN
AND WAS RAISED IN A RURAL FARMING COMMUNITY GROUNDED
IN HUMILITY AND HARD WORK ENCOURAGED BY HIS FATHER TO
PURSUE EDUCATION. >> DATO EXCELLED ACADEMICALLY,
GRADUATING AT THE TOP OF HIS CLASS AND EARNING A PLACE AT UT
IN ATENEO. THE TWO GUY GORO EXCUSE ME A
JESUIT BOARDING HIGH SCHOOL FAR FROM HOME.
HE LATER EARNED A BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN ELECTRICAL
ENGINEERING FROM THE MAPUA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY
IN MANILA. GRADUATING LAUDE IN 1968,
GORDO CAME TO THE UNITED STATES AS A DESIGN ENGINEER AT BOEING
CONTRIBUTING TO THE 747 JUMBO JET PROGRAM WHILE CONTINUING
HIS EDUCATION AT THE UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON WHERE HE MET HIS
FUTURE WIFE MARIA. HE WAS ACCEPTED INTO STANFORD'S
GRADUATE ENGINEERING PROGRAM IN 1970 AT STANFORD D'ORO
EARNED HIS MASTER'S DEGREE IN ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING
FOCUSED ON COMPUTER ARCHITECTURE AND SEMICONDUCTOR
SYSTEMS. HE WENT ON TO HOLD INFLUENTIAL
ENGINEERING ROLES IN NATIONAL SEMICONDUCTOR COMMODORE
INTERNATIONAL INTER CELL C TECHNOLOGY BRIDGING HARDWARE
AND SOFTWARE AT A TIME WHEN FEW COULD.
AS AN ENTREPRENEUR, PORCO FOUNDED CHIPS AND TECHNOLOGIES
WHERE HE DESIGNED THE WORLD'S FIRST SINGLE CHIP PC CHIPSET
WHICH ACCELERATED GLOBAL ACCESS TO PERSONAL COMPUTING.
HE THEN BECAME A RESPECTED VENTURE CAPITALIST OF THE
MAYFIELD FUND AND LATER FOUNDED TORCHWOOD VENTURE CAPITAL
MENTORING FOUNDERS INCLUDING INFLUENTIAL SEMICONDUCTOR
AND COMMUNICATIONS START UPS THAT HIS PROFESSIONAL
ACHIEVEMENTS WERE RECOGNIZED WITH MULTIPLE HONORS INCLUDING
ERNST AND YOUNG ENTREPRENEUR OF THE YEAR MULTIPLE APPEARANCES
ON THE FORBES LIST AND BEING FEATURED ON THE PHILIPPINE
POSTAGE STAMP FOR HIS CONTRIBUTIONS TO SCIENCE
AND TECHNOLOGY DEEPLY SHAPED BY HIS OWN JOURNEY FROM MODEST
BEGINNINGS TO GLOBAL IMPACT. DATO BONITO BELIEVED IN GIVING
BACK THROUGH EDUCATION AND INNOVATION.
HE WAS A KEY SUPPORTER OF THE CITRUS AND THE BONITO
INSTITUTE, A UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA RESEARCH CENTER
FOCUSED ON CREATING I.T SOLUTIONS THAT GENERATES
SOCIETAL AND ECONOMIC BENEFITS FOR EVERYONE.
THROUGH FOUNDING THE PHILIPPINE DEVELOPMENT FOUNDATION HE
EXPANDED ACCESS TO SCHOLARSHIPS, ENTREPRENEURSHIP
AND INNOVATION FOR YOUNG FILIPINOS AROUND THE GLOBE
AND THROUGH THE BONITO FAMILY FILIPINO AMERICAN EDUCATION
SCHOLARSHIP. CALIFORNIA RESIDENTS OF
FILIPINO DESCENT AND PURSUING STEM ARE ABLE TO GET SUPPORT
FOR THEIR COLLEGE EDUCATION. DATO IS SURVIVED BY HIS WIFE OF
53 YEARS MARIA. HIS CHILDREN AND THEIR SPOUSES
AND NINE CHERISHED GRANDCHILD ARIN INCLUDING LOCAL DISTRICT
TWO RESIDENTS TALABANI TAO, HIS DAUGHTER SON IN LAW THOMAS
KRONE AND GRANDSON LUCAS KELLY. FROM A FARMER'S SON TO A
SILICON VALLEY PIONEER AND GLOBAL PHILANTHROPIST DATO
BONITO EMBODIED THE PREMISE OF EDUCATION PERSEVERANCE
AND SERVICE TO OTHERS AND ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WE EXTEND OUR DEEPEST CONDOLENCES TO THE
ENTIRE FAMILY AND ALL WHO MOURN HIS PASSING.
MAY HIS MEMORY CONTINUE TO INSPIRE INNOVATION IN SERVICE
OF COMMUNITY. AN OPPORTUNITY FOR GENERATIONS
TO COME. >> THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR SHERYL SUPERVISOR
WALTON. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
CAN YOU PLEASE WE REFER WE REFER CERTAINLY.
SUPERVISOR HUANG I'M INTRODUCING A REQUEST FOR A
HEARING ON THE WIDESPREAD POWER OUTAGES THAT BEGAN ON DECEMBER
20TH AND LEFT NEARLY ONE THIRD OF SAN FRANCISCO WITHOUT
ELECTRIC CITY OF PERIODIC OUTAGES CONTINUING FOR SEVERAL
DAYS AND FULL POWER NOT RESTORED UNTIL DECEMBER 23RD.
THE SUNSET DISTRICT HAD SIX POWER OUTAGES IN THE MONTH OF
DECEMBER THIS WAS NOT A MINOR INCONVENIENCE.
FAMILIES LOST HEAT IN THE MIDDLE OF WINTER.
SENIORS WERE STRANDED IN THEIR HOMES.
ONE OF MY CONSTITUENTS, A 95 YEAR OLD MAN WHO RELIES ON A
VENTILATOR HAD TO BE RUSHED TO THE HOSPITAL AT TWO IN THE
MORNING. PEOPLE WATCHED THEIR PHONES DIE
WORRIED THEY'D LOSE THEIR ONLY CONNECTION TO 911 GARAGE DOORS
WOULDN'T OPEN. TRAFFIC LIGHTS WENT DARK
AND CAUSED CHAOS AT BETTY'S BUSY INTERSECTIONS.
SMALL BUSINESSES ON IRVING STREET HAD TO THROW AWAY
EVERYTHING IN THEIR REFRIGERATORS DURING ONE OF THE
BUSIEST WEEKS OF THE YEAR. THIS IS NOT THE FIRST TIME I'VE
RAISED CONCERNS OF JEANIE AFTER OUTAGES HIT SUNSET ON DECEMBER
7TH AND AGAIN ON DECEMBER 10TH. ON DECEMBER 11TH MY OFFICE SENT
A FORMAL LETTER ASKING FOR ANSWERS THAT THAT THE LEVEL OF
RELIABILITY IS UNACCEPTABLE. YET THE ROOT CAUSE OF THE
DECEMBER 20TH OUTAGE REMAINS UNDER INVESTIGATION.
THAT IS WHY WE NEED THIS HEARING.
OUR RESIDENTS DESERVE ANSWERS. THEY DESERVE TO KNOW WHY A
SUBSTATION FIRE NEAR MISSION AND 18TH CASCADED INTO AN
OUTAGE AFFECTING THE ENTIRE WESTERN HALF OF THE CITY.
THEY DESERVE TO KNOW WHAT ADDITIONAL COMPENSATION IS
AVAILABLE WHEN THE CURRENT CREDITS GENIE IS OFFERING $200
FOR RESIDENTS, $2,500 FOR BUSINESSES.
THEY NEED TO KNOW THAT THIS IS INADEQUATE TO COVER THE LOSSES
ACTUALLY SUFFERED SUFFERED AND THEY DESERVE TO KNOW WHAT
PGE IS DOING TO MAKE SURE THIS DOES NOT KEEP HAPPENING.
I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISORS MEHMOOD CHAN, CHERYL MELGAR
AND SADR FOR CO-SPONSORING THIS REQUEST.
I URGE THE PRESIDENT TO REFER THIS MATTER PROMPTLY SO WE CAN
GET ANSWERS FOR THE PEOPLE WE REPRESENT.
SECONDLY, IN ADDITION TO THE HEARING REQUESTS I JUST
INTRODUCED, I'M ALSO SUBMITTING A LETTER OF INQUIRY TO THE SAN
FRANCISCO PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION.
WHILE THE HEARING ON THE OUTAGES WILL HELP US UNDERSTAND
WHAT WENT WRONG ON DECEMBER 20TH, WE ALSO NEED TO
UNDERSTAND WHAT OPTIONS EXIST TO MAKE SURE THIS DOESN'T KEEP
HAPPENING. I KNOW THE CITY HAS BEEN
EXPLORING ACQUISITION OPPORTUNITIES, LOCAL
INFRASTRUCTURE FOR SEVERAL YEARS.
MY LETTER AS I SPOKE FOR A BRIEFING ON THE PRACTICAL
FISCAL AND OPERATIONAL CONSIDERATIONS TO ACQUIRE,
MAINTAIN AND OPERATE A PUBLICLY OWNED ELECTRIC GRID.
SO THIS BOARD CAN BE FULLY INFORMED AND POSITIONED TO ACT.
THIS IS ABOUT DOING OUR DUE DILIGENCE.
WHAT WOULD IT COST? WHAT FINANCING IS AVAILABLE?
DOES THE CITY HAVE THE CAPACITY TO OPERATE A GRID?
WHAT'S A REALISTIC TIMELINE? THIS INQUIRY WILL HELP US
UNDERSTAND WHAT'S WITHIN THE CITY'S POWER TO DO AND WHAT OUR
OPTIONS ARE MOVING THIS FORWARD.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU .
>> SUPERVISOR WONG. SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU,
MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY WITH EARLY
CO-SPONSORS FROM SUPERVISOR MAC DORSEY I'M INTRODUCED IN TWO
RESOLUTIONS TO HOLD PGE PACIFIC GAS AND ELECTRIC COMPANY
ACCOUNTABLE FOR THE BLACKOUTS THAT BEGAN ON DECEMBER 20TH OF
2025 AND AFFECTED OVER 130,000 CUSTOMERS FROM ACROSS THE
RICHMOND SUNSET ALL THE WAY TO CHINATOWN AND SOUTH TO MARKET.
THESE OUTAGES DISRUPTED SMALL BUSINESSES, SERIOUSLY IMPACTED
SENIORS, PEOPLE LIVING WITH DISABILITIES AND CAUSED PUBLIC
TRANSIT DELAYS AND STATION CLOSURES DURING THE HOLIDAY
WEEK. OVER THE COURSE OF THE HOLIDAY
BREAK THE RICHMOND DISTRICT ENDURED SIX POWER OUTAGES, SIX
POWER OUTAGES AND NOT TO MENTION THE SUBSTATION AT 24TH
AVENUE AND BALBOA CREATED A LOT OF DISTURBANCE FOR OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD FAMILIES HAVE TO DISPOSE GROCERIES WERE
REFRIGERATORS FILLED WITH HOLIDAYS, INGREDIENTS
AND ESSENTIALS. SOME OF THE MOST SIGNIFICANT
CONCERNS DURING THESE OUTAGES WERE THE IMPACT TO OUR
HOMEBOUND ELDERS AND RESIDENTS WHOSE HEALTH AND WELLNESS ARE
DEPENDENT ON RELIABLE ACCESS TO REFRIGERATED MEDICATIONS
AND OTHER SPECIAL CARE. THE FIRST RESOLUTION REAFFIRMS
THE CITY'S CONTINUING EFFORTS TO ACQUIRE AND USE
INFRASTRUCTURE DEEMED NECESSARY BY A 2019 REPORT FROM THE SAN
FRANCISCO PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION.
IN ORDER FOR THE CITY TO MEET OUR GOALS FOR AFFORDABLE, SAFE
AND RELIABLE POWER PROTECTION OF THE ENVIRONMENT
AND ACHIEVING CLIMATE GOALS, TRANSPARENCY AND PUBLIC
ACCOUNTABILITY, WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT AND EQUITABLE
ACCESS TO CLEAN, GREEN AND AFFORDABLE ELECTRIC POWER.
THESE BLACKOUTS ARE THE RESULT OF NEGLECTED INFRASTRUCTURE
MAINTENANCE BY PGE AND A PRIVATE COMPANY MORE INTERESTED
IN PROFITS AND RESOURCES FOR EXECUTIVE THAT OUTWEIGHS THEIR
CONCERNS FOR INVESTMENT IN SAFETY AND RELIABILITY.
THE SECOND RESOLUTION IS TO URGE GOVERNOR GAVIN NEWSOM
AND THE OFFICE OF ENERGY INFRASTRUCTURE SAFETY TO
WITHHOLD PGE SAFETY CERTIFICATES UNTIL ALL THE
INFRASTRUCTURE UNDER ITS CONTROL HAVE BEEN PROPERLY
INSPECTED AND MAINTAINED AND THAT INCLUDES SAN
FRANCISCO'S INFRASTRUCTURE. FOR TOO LONG P G HAS BEEN GIVEN
UNILATERAL CONTROL OVER THE STATE'S POWER GRID WITHOUT
BEING HELD ACCOUNTABLE FOR THE MAINTENANCE OF THE SYSTEM
LEADING TO DEVASTATING FIRES, LOSS OF LIFE AND CONTINUING
BLACKOUTS LEADING TO A LOSS OF PROPERTY AND INCOME.
THESE ONGOING PREVENTABLE DISASTERS AND FAILURE TO
UPGRADE AND IMPROVE ITS INFRASTRUCTURE PROVE THE
COMPANY CANNOT DELIVER ELECTRICITY TO OUR RESIDENTS
IN A SAFE WHERE LIABLE AND AFFORDABLE MANNER.
THEREFORE WE'RE URGING THE GOVERNOR TO HALT THE ISSUANCE
OF THEIR SAFETY CERTIFICATES FOR 2026 SO THAT PG AND G CAN
BE HELD ACCOUNTABLE FOR THESE FAILURES.
THEY MUST ANSWER OUR CALL AND AND OUR QUESTIONS UNTIL THE
GOVERNOR GRANT THEM THE SAFETY CERTIFICATE AND THE REST I
SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHAN. SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU,
MADAM CLERK. >> COLLEAGUE TODAY I'M
SUBMITTING A LETTER OF INQUIRY REGARDING THE SERVICES SUPPORT
SYSTEM FOR FIRE VICTIMS IN SAN FRANCISCO OVER 2025.
I'VE SEEN MANY FIRES IMPACTING HOMES AND APARTMENTS IN MY
DISTRICT AND THROUGHOUT THE CITY.
I'M REQUESTING INFORMATION REGARDING THE CITY'S PROTOCOLS
TO AGAIN TO ASSIST VICTIMS OF FIRE.
>> WHEN THIS DISASTER OCCURRED I AM DIRECTING THIS ALLY TO THE
SAN FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY
MANAGEMENT, THE HUMAN SERVICES AGENCY AND THE SAN FRANCISCO
POLICE DEPARTMENT. I'M REQUESTING DATA REGARDING
THE SERVICES THAT ARE PROVIDED TO FIRE VICTIMS.
>> PROTOCOLS FOR SERVICE DELIVERY LANGUAGE ACCESS AS
WELL AS DATA ON THE LEADING CAUSES AND RATE OF FIRES BY
DISTRICT. >> MY GOAL IS TO GAIN A BETTER
UNDERSTANDING OF THE GAPS AND NEEDS IN THE SERVICES THAT
WE CAN IMPROVE UPON TO SUPPORT TO FIRE VICTIMS WHEN THESE
TRAUMATIC INCIDENTS OCCUR. I WANT TO THANK MY LEGISLATIVE
AIDE CHARLIE FOR HIS WORK ON THIS.
SECONDLY, I ALSO WANT TO INTRODUCE A RESOLUTION
RECOGNIZING JANUARY 2026 AS NATIONAL HUMAN TRAFFICKING
PREVENTION MONTH HUMAN TRAFFICKING, LABOR AND SEX
TRAFFICKING ARE EXCEPTIONALLY PERVASIVE CRIMES THAT HAVE
MULTI-GENERATIONAL IMPACTS ON INDIVIDUALS AND FAMILIES
IMPACTING EVERYTHING FROM PUBLIC HEALTH TO HOUSING
SECURITY TO PUBLIC SAFETY AND MORE.
>> THIS YEAR THE SAN FRANCISCO BAY AREA WILL HOST TWO MAJOR
SPORTING EVENTS WITH THE NFL SUPER BOWL 60 AND FIFA WORLD
CUP. SAN FRANCISCO IS ANTICIPATING A
MASSIVE INFLUX IN TOURISM. HOTEL BOOKINGS PUTTING ON TO
OUR LOCAL BUSINESS AND MORE. >> WITH SUCH A SIGNIFICANT
INCREASE IN TRAVELERS, THERE ARE ALSO GROWING CONCERNS THAT
INCIDENTS OF HUMAN TRAFFICKING ARE TO INCREASE.
AS SUCH, IT'S IMPORTANT THAT WE BEGAN 2020 IS THIS BY
REAFFIRMING OUR CITY'S COMMITMENTS TO SURVIVORS OF
TRAFFICKING AND THE IMPACT TO COMMUNITIES AND COMMITTING TO
PRIORITIZE FUNDING AND RESOURCES FOR PROGRAMS
AND SERVICES THAT WORK TO PREVENT HUMAN TRAFFICKING
AND SUPPORT SURVIVORS? I WANT TO THANK ADVOCATES FOR
THEIR FEEDBACK ON THE RESOLUTION LANGUAGE SUPERVISOR
CHAN FOR HER PARTNERSHIP WRITING THIS RESOLUTION
AND OTHER CO-SPONSORS LIKE SUPERVISOR SUPERVISORS MELGAR
WALTON, DORSEY FIELDER, CHERYL MENTOR AND MOM WU AND WONG FOR
THEIR SUPPORT. AND ALSO THANK YOU TO MY
LEGISLATIVE LEGISLATIVE JACKIE FOR HER WORK ON THIS.
>> THE REST I SUMMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHEN SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU MADAM CLERK
ALTHOUGH I HAVE NOTHING TO INTRODUCE TODAY I WANTED TO ADD
MY VOICE TO SUPERVISOR CHANCE TO EXPRESS MY APPRECIATION FOR
HER LEADERSHIP ON THE NEED TO ONCE AND FOR ALL MUNICIPALITIES
ARE ELECTRIC UTILITY. I AM LIKEWISE APPRECIATIVE TO
SUPERVISOR WANG AND MAHMUD AND OTHERS FOR THEIR LEADERSHIP
IN CALLING FOR A HEARING AND I WOULD ASK TO JOIN AS A
CO-SPONSOR AND I WILL BE AN ENTHUSIASTIC PARTICIPANT WITH
SAN FRANCISCANS EXPERIENCE. OVER THE HOLIDAYS WAS THE
PREDICTABLE RESULT OF A PRIVATE UTILITY THAT HAS HISTORICALLY
FAILED TO INVEST IN SAFETY MAINTENANCE AND RELIABILITY.
AND IT'S WHY SAN FRANCISCO NEEDS A MUNICIPALLY OWNED
PUBLIC POWER SYSTEM. WHATEVER ELSE WE FIND OUT ABOUT
WHAT CAUSED THE DECEMBER 20TH OUTAGE, HERE'S A SPOILER ALERT.
IT'S BECAUSE PGE ANNIE IS AN INVESTOR OWNED UTILITY
ACCOUNTABLE TO SHAREHOLDERS BEFORE RATEPAYERS.
AND UNTIL THAT CHANGES WE CAN EXPECT MORE OF THE SAME JUST AS
WE HAVE FOR DECADES WITH TENS OF THOUSANDS OF RESIDENTS
AND BUSINESSES EXPERIENCING THE LOSS OF POWER FOR DAYS.
PUBLIC TRANSIT SHUTDOWNS SENIORS AND PEOPLE WITH
DISABILITIES LEFT WITHOUT EVEN THE MOST BASIC SERVICES.
THIS IS A SYSTEM FAILURE THAT IS UNACCEPTABLE.
AND THESE OUTAGES UNDERSCORE WHY SAN FRANCISCO MUST CONTINUE
TO MOVE FORWARD IN REALIZING THE PUBLIC POWER SYSTEM.
WE SHOULD HAVE HAD MORE THAN A CENTURY AGO SO THAT WE MAY ALL
BENEFIT FROM IMPROVED RELIABILITY PUBLIC SAFETY
ACCOUNTABILITY AND A UTILITY SYSTEM THAT IS FINALLY
ACCOUNTABLE TO RATEPAYERS AND NOT SHAREHOLDERS.
I WOULD EXPRESS MY APPRECIATION TO FORMER CITY ATTORNEY DENNIS
HERRERA AND CURRENT CITY ATTORNEY DAVID CHIU.
AND FOR ALL OF MY TO ALL OF MY FORMER CITY ATTORNEY COLLEAGUES
IN THAT OFFICE WHO HAVE WORKED ON THIS MUNICIPAL ASSOCIATION
EFFORT FOR MANY YEARS, WE ARE GOING TO GET THERE.
I AM PROUD TO CO-SPONSOR WITH SUPERVISOR CHAN THIS
RESOLUTION. BOTH RESOLUTIONS.
I THANK HER AGAIN FOR HER LEADERSHIP.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WONG, SUPERVISOR MACLEOD AND OTHERS
FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP AND MAKING AND I HOPE THAT THIS EFFORT
ENJOYS UNANIMOUS SUPPORT AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR DORSEY. WE WILL INTERRUPT ROLL CALL
AND COME BACK TO IT LATER. I WOULD NOTE THAT WE HAVE BEEN
JOINED IN THE CHAMBER BY FORMER SUPERVISOR SUSAN LAL WHO IS
HERE AND THAT'S WHERE IT'S ALSO CITY TREASURER AND GENERAL
MANAGER AND THEN WE ALSO HAVE OUR JUST OUR CURRENT DISTRICT
ATTORNEY BROOK JENKINS IS IN THE CHAMBER SO AS WELL AS
LOTS OF OTHER IMPORTANT PEOPLE .
>> MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL OUR 230 SPECIAL
ORDER? YES, THE 230 SPECIAL ORDER IS
THE RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATIONS FOR MERITORIOUS
SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> AND WE WILL START WITH DISTRICT SIX SUPERVISOR DORSEY
. THANK YOU, PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN
COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM HONORED TO RECOGNIZE OUR OUTGOING
INTERIM CHIEF OF POLICE PAUL YAP WITH THIS SPECIAL
COMMENDATION AND TO THANK HIM FOR HIS EXCEPTIONAL SERVICE TO
THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> CHIEF DART. STEP UP TO THE STEP UP TO THE
LECTERN AND THANKS. >> PAUL YAP IS A SAN FRANCISCAN
THROUGH AND THROUGH BORN AND RAISED IN THE CITY.
A GRADUATE OF LOWELL HIGH SCHOOL AND SAN FRANCISCO STATE
UNIVERSITY, PAUL'S CAREER REFLECTS A DEEP AND LASTING
COMMITMENT TO THE CITY HE LOVES AND THE COMMUNITIES THAT HAVE
HELPED TO SHAPE HIM. >> IN JANUARY 2025,
MAYOR DANIEL LEARY COAXED PAUL YAP OUT OF HIS POST S.F.
RETIREMENT TO SERVE AS HIS POLICY CHIEF FOR PUBLIC SAFETY.
BUT IN JUNE WITH THE DEPARTURE OF POLICE CHIEF BILL SCOTT, HE
WAS SELECTED TO SERVE AS SAN FRANCISCO'S INTERIM CHIEF OF
POLICE. NOW THOSE OF YOU HAVE HEARD ME
ADVOCATE FOR POLICE FULL STAFFING.
AS THE BROKEN RECORD I HAVE BEEN ON THAT ISSUE SINCE I GOT
HERE. YOU'VE HEARD ME TALK ABOUT THE
DISPROPORTIONATELY LARGE GENERATIONAL COHORT OF POLICE
OFFICERS REACHING RETIREMENT AGE.
THESE ARE THE BILL CLINTON ERA COPS HIRED BACK WHEN THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT HELPED LOCALITIES FUND POLICE HIRING
IN THE 90S. >> WELL, VIRTUALLY ALL OF THEM
ARE REACHING RETIREMENT AGE NOW AND SAN FRANCISCO IS NO
EXCEPTION. AND ALTHOUGH POLLY TEP YAPS
TENURE AS S.F. PD CHIEF WAS BRIEF, IT CAME AT A PIVOTAL
PIVOTAL TIME WITH A NUMBER OF HIGH RANKING RETIREMENTS.
AT A MOMENT WHEN SAN FRANCISCO NEEDED HIM MOST.
PAUL YEP EXPERIENCED LEADERSHIP IN OVERSEEING A GENERATIONAL
CHANGING OF THE GUARD AT SFPD WAS SIGNIFICANT AND VITALLY
IMPORTANT IN WAYS THAT WILL BENEFIT OUR CITY FOR YEARS TO
COME. PAUL BROUGHT MORE THAN 28 YEARS
OF LAW ENFORCEMENT EXPERIENCE TO HIS ROLE OVER THE COURSE OF
HIS CAREER WITH THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT.
IN FACT, HE SERVED AS COMMANDER AND THE CHIEF OF STAFF'S OFFICE
FOR OVERSEEING RISK MANAGEMENT AND STAFF SERVICES.
HE PREVIOUSLY LED CENTRAL NORTHERN AND RICHMOND STATIONS
AS WELL AS THE STAFF SERVICES DIVISION.
>> HE ALSO HELD SPECIALIZED ASSIGNMENTS IN DOMESTIC
VIOLENCE A VICE CRIMES HUMAN TRAFFICKING COMMUNITY RELATIONS
AND AS DIRECTOR OF BASIC TRAINING AT THE POLICE ACADEMY
AS A MEMBER OF THE POLICE COMMAND STAFF, PAUL PLAYED
IMPORTANT ROLES IN THE DEPARTMENT'S WORK ON 21ST
CENTURY POLICE REFORMS, POLICY DEVELOPMENT AND STRATEGIC
PLANNING. ABOVE ALL, HE IS MOST PROUD OF
HIS OUTREACH TO SAN FRANCISCO'S NEIGHBORHOODS FOR WHICH HE HAS
BEEN WIDELY RECOGNIZED FOR STRENGTHENING TRUST
AND ENGAGEMENT WITH DIVERSE COMMUNITIES ACROSS OUR CITY.
I RECALL THIS MYSELF DURING MY OWN TWO YEARS AS A CIVILIAN
MEMBER OF S.F. PD'S COMMAND STAFF DURING THE COVID CRISIS.
WITH THE MASSIVE COVID LOCKDOWNS THERE WERE A NUMBER
OF COMMUNITY BASED NEWS ORGANIZATIONS FACING VERY DIRE
FINANCIAL CONSEQUENCES IN SAN FRANCISCO.
AS THE COMMANDER OVERSEEING POLICE RECRUITMENT AT THE TIME,
PAUL YAP WORKED WITH ME TO MAKE SURE THAT S.F. PD FRONTLOADED
ITS RECRUITMENT ADVERTISING EXPENDITURE TO BETTER SUPPORT
OUR ETHNIC AND LGBTQ PLUS COMMUNITY BASED NEWS PARTNERS
WHEN THEY NEEDED IT MOST AND TO SUCCESSFULLY RECRUIT NO SMALL
NUMBER OF COMMUNITY BASED OFFICERS IN THE PROCESS.
>> HE BELIEVES, AS I DO, THAT REAL COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT MUST
ALSO INCLUDE COMMUNITY BASED JOURNALISM.
BUT DURING PAUL'S TIME AS INTERIM POLICE CHIEF, S.F. PD
DIDN'T JUST OVERSEE A CHANGING OF THE GUARD AMONG ITS COMMAND
RANKS, IT ALSO CONTINUED TO MAKE MEANINGFUL PROGRESS ON
PUBLIC SAFETY CITYWIDE MEASURED CRIME CATEGORIES FELL TO
HISTORIC LOWS REFLECTING THE DEDICATION OF OFFICERS ON THE
GROUND AND THE MORE EFFECTIVE USE OF VOTER APPROVED TOOLS.
PARTNERSHIPS WITH STATE, LOCAL AND FEDERAL AGENCIES WERE
STRENGTHENED AND FOR THE FIRST TIME SINCE THE ONSET OF THE
COVID PANDEMIC, S.F. PD SAW A NET INCREASE IN OFFICERS
PATROLLING SAN FRANCISCO STREETS AND NEIGHBORHOODS.
OUTSIDE OF HIS PROFESSIONAL LIFE.
PAUL IS A DEVOTED FAMILY MAN AND BAY AREA SPORTS FAN WHO
ENJOYS GOLFING, TRAVEL AND MARTIAL ARTS INTERESTS THAT
REFLECT HIS HARD WORK SELF-DISCIPLINE, INCLUSIVITY
AND BALANCE THAT WILL EXEMPLIFY HIS LEADERSHIP.
FOR SAN FRANCISCO WAS FORTUNATE TO HAVE A STEADY HAND AND DEEP
EXPERIENCE GUIDING OUR POLICE DEPARTMENT EVEN FOR A SHORT
TIME. YOUR DEDICATION TO PUBLIC
SAFETY AND TO THE CITY HAS LEFT A LASTING IMPRESSION.
>> ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND THE PEOPLE OF
THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO, IT IS MY PRIVILEGE
AND HONOR TO HONOR YOU WITH THE UNIVERSALLY RECOGNIZED REWARD
FOR EXCELLENCE IN POLICING DONUTS.
SO I CONGRATULATIONS. CONGRATULATION.
>> AS CHIEF CHEF AND I HAVE SOME COLLEAGUES AND I THINK
SOME OTHERS WHO WOULD LIKE TO SAY A FEW WORDS.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR DORSEY?
YES, CHIEF? >> YEP.
YOU SHOULD SETTLE IN BECAUSE THERE'S A LONG LINE OF PEOPLE
WHO WANT TO TALK. >> SO SUPERVISOR MAHMUD, IF YOU
JUST WANTED TO THANK YOU OVER THIS YEAR OF WORKING WITH YOU
IN PARTNERSHIP ECHOING EVERYTHING THAT SUPERVISOR
DORSEY SAID. >> BUT I THINK A COUPLE THINGS
ANSWER KNOWLEDGE AS WELL AS THAT THE SPEED AT WHICH YOU
INSTITUTED CHANGES THAT I THINK HAVE LONG BEEN SOUGHT IN THE
CITY HAVE LED TO THE OUTCOMES THAT SUPERVISOR DORSEY
MENTIONED. I CAN JUST SPEAK FROM FROM OUR
DISTRICT'S PERSPECTIVE IN DISTRICT FIVE WHEN THERE WAS
A STRING OF BURGLARIES IN THE FILLMORE.
YOU AND I WORK TOGETHER AND YOU IMMEDIATELY PUT IN POLICE
AMBASSADORS THAT HAVEN'T BEEN SEEN IN THE FILLMORE VALLEY
IN YEARS. >> I KNOW IN THE TENDERLOIN
WHERE A COMMUNITY THAT HAS BEEN ASKING FOR BEAT OFFICERS FOR
YEARS AND THERE'S BEEN NO INCREASE.
YOU WORK WITH CAPTAIN SULLIVAN AND I DON'T KNOW HOW YOU GUYS
DID IT SO FAST WHAT PEOPLE HAVE BEEN ASKING FOR SO LONG BUT IT
JUST SHOWED THAT YOU LISTEN. YOU LISTEN TO THE NEEDS OF THE
COMMUNITY, LISTEN TO THE NEEDS OF THE OF THE DISTRICT AND SOME
OF THE MOST VULNERABLE COMMUNITIES IN THE ENTIRE CITY.
AND THESE ARE PERMANENT CHANGES THAT ARE NOW GOING TO BENEFIT
THE RESIDENTS OF DISTRICT FIVE AND SAN FRANCISCO BECAUSE OF
YOUR TENURE AND LISTENING TO COMMUNITY AND WORKING ON BEHALF
OF THIS COMMUNITY AS WELL. AND SO I JUST AGAIN COMMEND THE
SPEED THAT YOU'VE WORKED OUT, HOW YOU'VE LISTENED TO
COMMUNITY AND REALLY MADE STRIDES ON REBUILDING OUR RANKS
BUT ALSO IN TAKING STEPS TOWARDS SOLVING OUR DRUG CRISIS
AS WELL. AND I KNOW THE TENDERLOIN
FILLMORE HAS VALLEY ALL THE WAY HAIGHT ASHBURY AND DISTRICT
FIVE EXTREMELY GRATEFUL FOR YOUR SERVICE.
>> AND I WANT YOU TO KNOW THIS WON'T BE THE LAST YOU SEE ME AS
WELL. ON A PERSONAL NOTE, CHIEF YAP
AND I SHARE THE SAME MY TIE INSTRUCTOR AND I MADE A NEWS
RESOLUTION TO COME BACK THIS YEAR.
SO PLEASE GO EASY ON ME. SO THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR CHERYL YEAH, I WAS KIND OF FIGURE OUT WHAT I
SHOULD ADDRESS YOU AS ARE YOU, CHIEF AND THEN I REALIZE YOU'RE
STILL CHIEF. SO AS A POLICY CHIEF OR AS
INTERIM POLICE CHIEF, YOUR SERVICE TO THE CITY IS JUST.
THANK YOU. IT IS NO SMALL THING TO COME
OUT OF RETIREMENT TO CONTINUE TO SERVE THIS CITY AND THAT WAS
A HUGE LEAP OF FAITH THAT YOU TOOK AND WE ARE ALL THE BETTER
FOR IT. AND SO FIRST OF ALL, THANK YOU
FOR THAT. SECOND, I WANT TO ECHO
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD'S REMARKS ON SPEED.
SPEED TO ACTION IS INCREDIBLY IMPORTANT AND YOU HAD THAT
IN SPADES AND THANK YOU. AND I ESPECIALLY WANT TO THANK
YOU FOR YOUR PARTNERSHIP ON TWO VERY CRITICAL THINGS IN MY
DISTRICT THAT MAYBE DON'T GET ENOUGH ATTENTION BUT YOU PAID
ATTENTION TO THEM. THE FIRST WAS YOUR SUPPORT OF
THE PLANNED PARENTHOOD SITE ON BUSH STREET.
YOU AND YOUR COMMAND STAFF WERE FANTASTIC IN RESPONDING THERE
AND I JUST WANT TO THANK YOU FOR YOUR ATTENTION TO THAT
AND ALSO FOR YOUR ATTENTION ON A PROJECT THAT MAY SEEM SMALL
BUT HAS ALREADY SAVED LIVES AND THAT'S CREATING THE FIRST
IN THE NATION SAFE GUN STORAGE PROGRAM IN CONJUNCTION WITH
PIERCE'S PLEDGE. YOU TOOK SOMETHING THAT EASILY
COULD HAVE BEEN HELD UP IN BUREAUCRACY AND WELL, I
DON'T KNOW MAYBE. WELL, WE GOT TO SEE AND YOU
MADE IT HAPPEN QUICKLY. THAT'S REAL LEADERSHIP.
AND I JUST WANT TO THANK YOU FOR YOUR SERVICE AND YOUR
CONTINUED LEADERSHIP AND IT'S GREAT TO KNOW YOU'RE NOT GOING
ANYWHERE. >> THANK YOU, SIR.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU,
PRESIDENT AMENDMENT AND I WILL SAY CHIEF STILL THANK YOU JUST
FOR ALL YOUR THE THINGS THAT YOU HAVE DONE.
I THINK THAT WHEN YOU STEP UP TO THE PLATE TO RETURN BACK TO
CITY HALL AND KNEW THAT IT WAS NOT GOING TO BE EASY.
AS OUR PUBLIC SAFETY CHIEF OR THE MAYOR AND ADVISOR TO THE
MAYOR, YOU KNEW THAT THE JOB WAS DIFFICULT BUT YOU CAME BACK
AND YOU MAKE SURE THAT IT WAS A GOOD TRANSITION.
AND I TRULY BELIEVE THAT YOU DID THAT IN THE BEST INTERESTS
OF THE CITY AND TRULY AGAIN YOU DEMONSTRATED IT SO OFTEN TIME A
LOT OF PEOPLE QUESTIONS OUR INTENTION THE THINGS THAT WE DO
HERE INSIDE CITY HALL. BUT I THINK THAT YOU HAVE
DEMONSTRATED SINCE YOUR RETURN BACK TO THE DEPARTMENT BUT THAT
YOU REALLY WERE DOING THIS IN THE BEST INTERESTS OF OUR
CITY. YOU NOT ONLY THAT FOR ALL THE
THINGS THAT YOU HAVE DONE THROUGH BUDGET AND DURING THE
TIME OF BUDGET AND THROUGH ALL THE REFORMS IS THAT YOU HAVE
ALSO DEMONSTRATED THAT IT WAS ALWAYS BEEN YOUR INTENTION TO
NURTURE THE NEXT GENERATION OF LEADERSHIP WITHIN THE
DEPARTMENT AND THAT IT SHOWS THAT FROM THE RANK AND FILE TO
ALL YOUR COMMANDERS AND YOUR DEPUTY CHIEF THROUGHOUT THE
TIME WHEN YOU WERE OUR ACTING CHIEF TO NOW THAT WE NOW HAVE
CHIEF DEREK LEW AS OUR NEW CHIEF.
ALL THESE WERE WORK BECAUSE OF YOUR LEADERSHIP AND THAT YOU
HAVE DONE THAT SELFLESSLY. SO FOR THAT WE'RE GRATEFUL
AND THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR WORK.
>> SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU BOTH.
PRESIDENT. THANK YOU CHIEF YAP I OBSERVE
ALMOST ONE YEAR SUPERVISOR I FIRSTLY WANT TO THANK YOU FOR
ALL YOUR SUPPORT YOU KNOW COMING TO DISTRICT 11 MULTIPLE
TIMES TO WALK. WANT TO TALK WITH THE MERCHANTS
AND ALSO COMING TO SUPPORT OUR EVENTS IN DISTRICT 11.
YOUR LEADERSHIP AND AND YOUR DEDICATION OF KEEPING SAN
FRANCISCO SAFE WITHOUT WORDS THAT CAN REALLY DESCRIBE BUT
THANK YOU THAT IT'S PROVEN AND IT'S KEEPING SAN FRANCISCO
SAFE AND OUR CITY IS ON THE RISE AS THE MAYORS USUALLY SAY
THIS WORD. BUT I ALSO WANT TO SAY A FEW
WORDS TO THANK YOUR WIFE AND CHILDREN'S FOR SHARING YOU
AND AND ALL THE SACRIFICES THAT YOU MAKE FROM FAMILY TIME
AND IT'S REALLY VALUABLE AND ALSO, YOU KNOW, ALL THOSE
SACRIFICES REALLY MAKES IT ALSO INVALUABLE TO MAKE SURE THAT
YOU ARE ABLE TO CONTINUE TO, YOU KNOW, SERVE YOUR ROLE
KEEPING SAN FRANCISCO SAFE AND OUR COMMUNITY IS VERY PROUD
OF YOU. I AM VERY PROUD OF YOU.
SO I WANT TO ALSO THINK THAT AND A VERY PERSONAL NOTE AS I
ACTUALLY MADE IT TO YOUR THIS FOR ONE OF YOUR FAVORITE
SUPERVISORS. SO I AM VERY HAPPY FOR THAT
AND I AM ALSO VERY MUCH MISS ALL THOSE PROMOTION EVENTS
IN THE LAST DECADE THAT I WAS PART OF YOUR COMMAND OR CONTROL
AND ALL THOSE BANQUETS I FOR YEARS AND THEN WE'RE GOING TO
CONTINUE TO CELEBRATE YOU BUT I DO LOOK FORWARD CONTINUE TO
CELEBRATE WITH YOU AGAIN AT FIVE YEARS WITHOUT ADD A TITLE
AND ACHIEVEMENT. AND WITH THAT I ALSO WANT TO
THANK AGAIN THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR ALL THAT YOU HAVE DONE.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR SAUTER CHIEF YEP.
>> THANK YOU FOR STEPPING UP IN THIS PAST YEAR I THINK
IN THIS PAST YEAR YOU WERE PUT IN ASKED OFFERED IN TWO
DIFFERENT REALLY REALLY CRITICAL ROLES FOR OUR CITY
AND IN A SHORT YEAR WE ALL SEE AND WE FEEL THE IMPACT OF YOUR
WORK. IT'S REMARKABLE AND I HAVE
GREAT RESPECT FOR YOU FOR STEPPING FORWARD IN IN BOTH OF
THOSE DIFFERENT ROLES IN THIS PAST YEAR.
YOU KNOW, I THINK THAT, YOU KNOW, AS OTHERS SHARED, THE
THING I RESPECT MOST ABOUT YOU IS THAT YOU YOU GET TOUGH
PROBLEMS PUT BEFORE YOU AND YOU FIELD TOUGH CALLS FROM US.
BUT DESPITE THAT YOU LOOK FOR YOU LOOK FOR ANSWERS AND YOU
LOOK FOR OUTCOMES. YOU DON'T MAKE EXCUSES WHEN YOU
COULD MAKE EXCUSES AND YOU ALWAYS TRY AND FIGURE OUT A WAY
TO IMPROVE THINGS AND YOU'VE DONE THAT FOR MY CONSTITUENTS,
FOR MY COMMUNITIES IN DISTRICT THREE MANY TIMES IN THIS PAST
YEAR. SO I REALLY APPRECIATE ALL OF
THAT WORK EVERYTHING YOU'VE DONE THIS PAST YEAR BUT
EVERYTHING YOU'VE DONE FOR OUR CITY, THE WORK WE DID ALMOST A
DECADE AGO NOW WHEN YOU WERE AT CENTRAL STATION YOU KNOW FOLKS
STILL REMEMBER THE IMPACT YOU HAD THERE AND STILL SPEAK
FONDLY OF YOU AND IN THAT DISTRICT THREE COMMUNITY.
SO THANK YOU FOR EVERYTHING. I KNOW YOU WON'T BE GOING FAR
AND AND I LOOK FORWARD TO ALL THE TIME AHEAD AND THANK YOU
AGAIN CHIEF SUPERVISOR WONG OKAY AND THANK YOU CHIEF.
I'LL KEEP IT SHORT BUT JUST WANT TO THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR
BEING A TRUE PUBLIC SERVANT BEING ABLE TO COME BACK TO
SERVING THE CITY AND BEING WILLING TO STEP UP INTO THE
ROLES THAT YOU HAVE AND ALSO OVER THE PAST YEARS SEEING THE
DRASTIC CHANGES AND IMPROVEMENTS IN PUBLIC
SAFETY. IT'S A REAL CREDIT TO YOUR
LEADERSHIP TO TO THE COMMUNITY AND TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF
SAN FRANCISCO. >> SO THOSE ARE AND ALSO BEING
ABLE TO TAKE INNOVATIVE APPROACHES IN LAW ENFORCEMENT
AND BEING ABLE TO BRING A LEVEL OF PROFESSIONALISM AND PRIDE TO
THE PROFESSION. SO REALLY APPRECIATE YOUR WORK
AND I'M LOOKING FORWARD TO CONTINUE WORKING WITH YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU, CHIEF.
JUST WANT TO ECHO THE SENTIMENTS OF MY COLLEAGUES BUT
ALSO REALLY APPRECIATE YOU FOR IN YOUR SHORT TIME AS THE CHIEF
FOR NOT ONLY BEING RESPONSIVE BUT ACTUALLY LISTENING
AND UNDERSTANDING THAT TERMINOLOGY MATTERS.
WE HAD CONVERSATIONS ABOUT THINGS THAT AFFECT COMMUNITY
AND HOW OFFICERS RESPOND AND TO CERTAIN COMMUNITIES AND WE
WORKED TOGETHER TO MAKE THOSE CHANGES AND YOU WERE VERY
RESPONSIVE AND AMENABLE TO TO HAVING THOSE CONVERSATIONS.
SO ONE APPRECIATES YOU NOT JUST FOR THAT BUT OBVIOUSLY FOR ALL
THE WORK YOU'VE DONE HERE IN YOUR ROLE AS A POLICE
OFFICER IN THIS CITY. THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU PRESIDENT THANK YOU SUPERVISOR
DORSEY FOR THIS. CHIEF YEP.
THANK YOU. ACTUALLY FOR A LIFETIME OF
DEDICATION TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO FOR
THIS IDEA PARTICULARLY FOR THE LAST TWO JOBS I'VE HELD THAT I
HAVE PERSONALLY BENEFITED FROM YOUR GREAT COMPETENCE
AND WISDOM AND ALSO YOUR EXPERIENCE, YOUR LIFE
EXPERIENCE THAT YOU HAVE BROUGHT TO THIS JOB.
AS SOMEBODY WHO WAS BORN HERE AND YOU KNOW LIKE KNOWS THE
COMMUNITY INSIDE AND OUT IN ALL OF THE DIFFERENT UNIVERSES THAT
EXIST SIDE BY SIDE IN SAN FRANCISCO BECAUSE
REPRESENTATION MATTERS AND ALSO EXPERIENCE MATTERS.
SO THANK YOU FOR ALL OF THAT. AND I WANT TO SAY THAT, YOU
KNOW, LEADERSHIP IS DIFFICULT AS SOME OF MY COLLEAGUES HAVE
SAID. PEOPLE QUESTION OUR DECISIONS
AND OUR MOTIVATIONS SO IT IS DIFFICULT TO BE IN THOSE
POSITIONS THAT YOU'VE HELD. BUT BEING A TRANSITIONAL LEADER
IS EVEN MORE DIFFICULT BECAUSE IT'S A THING IN AND OF ITSELF.
YOU KNOW, PEOPLE QUESTION YOU EVEN MORE AND ANY CHANGES THAT
YOU MAKE PEOPLE ARE LIKE WHY? YOU KNOW SO AND YOU HAVE DONE
IT WITH GRACE AND ELEGANCE AND RESPECT FOR THE REST OF US.
AND SO I JUST WANT TO THANK YOU FOR THE STEPPING UP BUT ALSO
THE ROLE THAT YOU PLAYED IN THE HISTORY OF OUR CITY.
>> SO THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR I, I THINK EVERYTHING HAS BEEN SAID BUT I
WOULD ADD AS THE WARM UP ACT FOR THE MAYOR THAT THAT CHIEF
STEPPED IN TO THIS ROLE AT A UNIQUELY IMPORTANT MOMENT FOR
THE POLICE DEPARTMENT HAVING BEEN THROUGH A SIGNIFICANT
PERIOD OF REFORM THAT WAS HARD BUT ALSO NOW DEALING WITH
INCREASING DEMANDS FROM THE PUBLIC FOR A RENEWED FOCUS ON
THE BASICS OF SAFETY AND HAVING TO BALANCE ALL OF THE COMPETING
CLAIMS MADE ON YOUR DEPARTMENT THAT WOULD BE CHALLENGING AT
ANY TIME AND I THINK ESPECIALLY OVER THIS LAST YEAR.
SO WE'RE VERY, VERY GRATEFUL THAT YOU'VE STEPPED FORWARD.
I THINK IT IS A MARK OF OF THE RESPECT THAT IS FOR YOU NOT
JUST THE FOLKS FROM THE COMMUNITY ARE HERE, NOT JUST
YOUR CAPTAINS AND COMMAND STAFF WHO SHOWED UP BUT ALSO THAT
YOUR ELECTED PUBLIC SAFETY PARTNERS, OUR DISTRICT ATTORNEY
AND OUR SHERIFF ARE BOTH HERE AND I'M GOING TO INVITE EACH OF
THEM TO SPEAK BEFORE YOU DO AND SEE.
>> YEAH, BUT FIRST I'M GOING TO INVITE THE MAYOR TO COME
FORWARD AND SAY A FEW WORDS. >> WELL, MAYOR LURIE, THANK YOU
BOARD PRESIDENT TO THE SUPERVISORS.
HAPPY NEW YEAR. IT'S GOOD TO SEE YOU ALL.
>> MY GOODNESS. PAUL, WHY ARE ALL THESE PEOPLE
HERE FOR YOU? >> IT'S A TESTAMENT IT'S A
TESTAMENT TO YOUR 28 YEARS OF SERVICE.
I REMEMBER GETTING TO KNOW YOU. WE WOULD GO ON WALKS
IN CHINATOWN AND THROUGH YOUR OLD DISTRICT AND WE LITERALLY
COULDN'T GO A HALF A BLOCK WITHOUT PEOPLE BEING LIKE
CAPTAIN CAPTAIN OR YOU KNOW, JUST SAYING PAUL, WE MISS YOU
AND AND EVERYBODY WOULD SAY THANK YOU.
AND I JUST YOU KNOW, THE SUPERVISOR SAYS HAVE ALL SAID
IT VERY ELOQUENTLY YOU CAME IN DURING A VERY A TIME OF
TRANSITION FOR THE DEPARTMENT YOU NOT ONLY GAVE ME A LOT OF
STRENGTH AND SUPPORT, YOU GAVE THIS DEPARTMENT STRENGTH
AND SUPPORT WHEN IT NEEDED IT. YOU ARE A BRIDGE TO THIS NEXT
GENERATION OF LEADERSHIP HERE THAT IS ALL AROUND AND THIS
DEPARTMENT IS IN INCREDIBLE SHAPE AND A LOT OF THAT CREDIT
GOES TO YOU AND TO YOUR LEADERSHIP.
I COULD GO ON AND ON. I WON'T DO THAT BECAUSE THERE'S
A LOT OF PEOPLE THAT WANT TO SAY A LOT OF NICE THINGS ABOUT
YOU BUT IT'S AN HONOR TO BE ABLE TO CALL YOU NOT ONLY CHIEF
BUT ALSO A DEAR FRIEND SOMEONE THAT REALLY HELPED MAKE SAN
FRANCISCO IN 2025 THE SAFEST IN MANY RESPECTS ON RECORD
SINCE THE 1950S. THAT IS A TESTAMENT TO YOUR
LEADERSHIP AND TO EVERYBODY AT THE CPD WHO IS BEHIND ME
AND BEHIND YOU AND I WISH YOU I KNOW YOU'RE NOT GOING ANYWHERE.
SO EXPECT THOSE LATE NIGHT PHONE CALLS FOR ME TO CONTINUE
AND ON BEHALF OF A GRATEFUL CITY WE ARE INDEBTED TO YOU.
WE APPRECIATE YOU AND WE SAY THANK YOU AND THIS HONOR
AND THIS RECOGNITION IS WELL DESERVED.
SO THANK YOU FOR PRESIDENT AND THANK YOU TO THE
SUPERVISORS FOR HONORING HIM TODAY.
>> THANK YOU ALL. NOT YET, CHIEF YET DISTRICT
ATTORNEY BROOKE JENKINS. >> COME ON UP BECAUSE SO I
DON'T KNOW WHAT YOU WERE THINKING A NUMBER OF MONTHS
AGO. I REMEMBER AFTER AFTER I GOT
APPOINTED I WAS LIKE WHAT WAS I THINKING?
WHAT DID I JUST STEP INTO? AND THERE IS NO HARDER THING TO
DO THAN TO FOLLOW A POLICE CHIEF THAT WAS HERE FOR EIGHT
YEARS THE LONGEST I THINK ON RECORD BUT ALSO AT A TIME WITH
A BRAND NEW MAYOR AND MULTIPLE BRAND NEW BOARD MEMBERS WHO ALL
I'M SURE CALLED YOU CONSTANTLY ABOUT WHAT A SPEEDY NEEDED TO
DO TO SERVE NOT ONLY THE ENTIRE CITY FOR THE MAYOR BUT EACH
INDIVIDUAL DISTRICT. AND SO I REALLY DO WANT TO
POINT OUT THAT YOU CAME IN AT A TIME WHERE IT COULDN'T HAVE
BEEN MORE CHALLENGING JUST AS THE PERSON IN LEADERSHIP TO
HAVE SO MANY DEMANDS PLACED ON YOU AND YOU KNOW, AS MOST
PEOPLE KNOW, CHIEF SCOTT AND I WERE VERY CLOSE AND IT WAS A
SIGNIFICANT FEELING THAT I HAD OBVIOUSLY WHEN HE LEFT AND NOT
KNOWING, YOU KNOW, WHAT WAS TO COME FOR THE PARTNERSHIP
AND THE RELATIONSHIP THAT WOULD BE BUILT BETWEEN ME AND WHOEVER
TOOK OVER. AND I HAVE TO SAY IN THIS ROOM
THAT FROM DAY ONE YOU REACHED OUT TO ME AND YOU WERE A
TREMENDOUS PARTNER. YOU CALLED ME ABOUT EVERYTHING
THAT YOU THOUGHT I NEEDED TO KNOW OR BE A PART OF AND SO FOR
THAT I HAVE TO JUST SHOW MY APPRECIATION FOR YOU BECAUSE I
DON'T TAKE THAT FOR GRANTED. I KNOW THIS CITY DOESN'T TAKE
IT FOR GRANTED. THEY'VE SEEN FAR TOO MANY
DECADES OF DA'S AND POLICE CHIEFS NOT GETTING ALONG AND SO
I THINK THAT'S A TRUE TESTAMENT TO YOUR LEADERSHIP AND TO YOUR
SELFLESSNESS NOT ONLY TO TAKE OVER THE HELM FOR THAT INTERIM
PERIOD BUT ALSO TO SERVE IN THE WAY THAT THE CITY CONTINUED TO
NEED. SO I AM JUST SO GRATEFUL FOR
YOU AND THE FACT THAT WE WERE ABLE TO PUSH THROUGH THIS SO
SEAMLESSLY AND CONTINUE TO MAKE SAN FRANCISCO SAFER BECAUSE I
COULDN'T DO THAT ON MY OWN CERTAINLY.
BUT ALSO I SEE SO MANY COMMUNITY MEMBERS HERE
PARTICULARLY FROM CHINATOWN AND THE ASIAN COMMUNITY
AND LOOK, IT'S BEEN A ROUGH ROAD FOR SOME TIME IN THIS CITY
FOR PARTICULARLY OUR ASIAN SENIORS BUT THE OVERALL
COMMUNITY AND I KNOW WHAT IT MEANT TO SO MANY PEOPLE IN THIS
ROOM TO HAVE YOU AS THE LEADER AND WHAT YOU HAVE DONE TO
RE-INSTILL A LEVEL OF CONFIDENCE THAT THAT NEEDS WILL
BE MET. AND SO I JUST WANTED TO POINT
THAT OUT BECAUSE IT HASN'T BEEN SAID BUT TO MAKE SURE THAT WE
SEE THAT AND I KNOW SO MANY PEOPLE FEEL THAT AND THAT'S WHY
THEY'RE HERE AND SO THANK YOU AND VICE VERSA.
I SEE YOU IN THE QUEUE. >> I WAS GOING TO OFFER SHERIFF
MIYAMOTO AN OPPORTUNITY TO SPEAK WITH YOU TO SHARE WITH ME
MOTO YOU KNOW I'M GOING TO BREAK FROM EVERYTHING THAT
EVERYONE'S BEEN SAYING AND I'M JUST I'M VERY DISAPPOINTED
YOU'RE LEAVING BECAUSE NOW I HAVE TO WORK WITH TWO
INDIVIDUALS FROM S.I., TWO WILDCATS WHEN WE HAD THEM
OUTNUMBERED AS LOWLIGHTS. SO BUT I WILL SAY REGARDLESS OF
WHAT SCHOOLS WE COME FROM OR OUR BACKGROUNDS WHEN WE ALL
COME TOGETHER IN PUBLIC SAFETY ,WE'RE DOING IT OUT OF OUR
HEART, OUT OF OUR MIND AND SPIRIT.
AND YOU BROUGHT THAT TO THE TABLE.
I WAS NOTHING BUT HONORED TO WORK WITH YOU AND IN
RECOGNITION OF THAT I WILL NOT SHARE ANY STORIES OF OUR TIME
AT UC DAVIS TOGETHER BECAUSE ALTHOUGH THE STATUTE OF
LIMITATIONS HAS RUN OUT THAT PROBABLY WOULDN'T BE A GOOD
THING TO SAY IN FRONT OF ALL THESE PEOPLE.
SO THANK YOU FOR THE WORK YOU'VE DONE AND FOR JUST BEING
A FRIEND. AND NOW BEFORE WE INVITE CHIEF
YAP TO SPEAK SUPERVISOR DORSEY SO AS THE PRESENTING SUPERVISOR
I'M GOING TO INVOKE THE DISTRICT SIX PRIVILEGE TO
INVITE A PUBLIC SAFETY PARTNER IN RUDY CORPUS FROM UNITED
PLAYERS TO JUST BRIEFLY I KNOW TAKES FIRST OFF HAPPY NEW YEAR
ALL THE SUPERVISORS PRESIDENT AMANO ME.
THANKS FOR HAVING ME SHARE I'M FROM SAN FRANCISCO BORN
AND RAISED AND I'M HONORED TO SPEAK ON A BROTHER MY RIGHT
HERE AND SOMEBODY WHO LIVED ON THE OTHER SIDE OF THE GUN WHO'S
AN EX-FELON TOO FOR ME TO COME HERE AND SPEAK AND SAY HOW
PROUD I AM OF YOU IS TO ME IS KIND OF FOREIGN RIGHT?
>> BUT I COME HERE BECAUSE I BELIEVE IN INTEGRITY, LOYALTY,
HONOR AND ALL THE VALUES THAT A HUMAN BEING SHOULD HAVE WHICH
YOU HAVE. >> PAUL AND THAT'S WHY I MEANT
WHEN I STARTED DOING THIS WORK IT TOOK ME A LONG TIME TO BUILD
RELATIONSHIPS WITH THE POLICE BECAUSE WHEN I GREW UP WE
DIDN'T TRUST THE POLICE AND TO HAVE SOMEBODY LIKE YOU THAT I
MET THAT WAS IN A FORCE IT WAS EASY BECAUSE YOU HAD ALL THOSE
VALUES AS A HUMAN BEING AND SO I RESPECT YOU.
YOU KNOW, THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR WHAT YOU HAVE BEEN DOING FOR
THIS WHOLE CITY BECAUSE LAST MONTH AT THE END OF THE YEAR
ME, YOU THIS GUY RIGHT HERE THE DAY WE GOT OVER TO 130 GUNS OFF
THE STREETS OF SAN FRANCISCO IN WHICH YOUR TEAM WITH YOUR
TEAM HERE WHO'S BEEN DOING A GREAT JOB BECAUSE THEY DOING
THIS WORK NOW I UNDERSTAND AND SEE THAT BEING POLICE
OFFICERS IS PROBABLY ONE OF THE HARDEST JOBS YOU CAN HAVE ON
THIS PLANET. I COULDN'T DO WHAT YOU GUYS DO
SO THAT'S OUT TO THE CAPTAIN, RIGHT?
>> THEY WILL SAY ANY PLAYER AND SO I JUST WANT TO SAY THANK
YOU SO MUCH FOR WHAT YOU HAVE CONTRIBUTE TO THIS PLANET, THIS
CITY FOR THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO AND I LOOK FORWARD TO
MEETING AND WORK AND CONTINUE TO WORKING WITH YOU OR A NEW
CHIEF THAT'S IN PLACE BECAUSE I BELIEVE IN YOU GUYS, MY BROTHER
I REALLY DO. AND FOR SOMEBODY WHO WAS LIKE I
SEE IT AS AN EX-FELON I GOT A LOT OF RESPECT FOR YOU BROTHER.
>> IT'S ALL THE HOMIES TOLD ME MAN.
>> THEY TELL YOU WHAT'S UP? >> ALL RIGHT.
SUPERVISED, SUPERVISED. >> DORSEY CAN WE LET THE MAN
SPEAK? I THINK I THANK YOU.
I SHOULD I WOULD LIKE TO. >> WE DO HAVE AT LEAST ONE
POLICE COMMISSIONER. I SEE LARRY OUT THERE AND I SEE
A NUMBER OF CITY COMMISSIONERS WHO HAVE SHOWED UP FOR YOU,
CHIEF. YEAH, CHIEF.
>> YEP. GREAT.
THANK YOU. PRESIDENT MIDDLEMAN.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MATT DORSEY FOR THIS HONOR AND FOR
THE DONUTS ESPECIALLY AND THANK YOU TO OUR SUPERVISORS FOR ALL
YOUR KIND WORDS. IT MEANS A LOT AND I HAVE
REALLY ENJOYED WORKING WITH YOU AT THIS IN THIS CAPACITY AND I
JUST HAVE TO TELL YOU AND THE PUBLIC THAT I HAVE THE UTMOST
RESPECT FOR WHAT YOU DO AND I CAN TELL YOU UPFRONT AND BEHIND
THE SCENES THAT YOU ARE ABSOLUTELY PRO YOUR
COMMUNITIES. YOU FIGHT FOR THEM AND I'M JUST
PROUD TO STAND BESIDE YOU FOR THAT FIGHT FOR YOUR COMMUNITY
SO THANK YOU FOR ALL YOU'VE DONE FOR FOR SAN FRANCISCO AS A
LONG TIME ENFORCEMENT AND PUBLIC SAFETY PROFESSIONAL
IT IS ALWAYS HUMBLING A HUMBLING EXPERIENCE TO HEAR
WHEN OTHERS LIST YOUR ACCOMPLISHMENTS.
SO THANK YOU FOR THAT. >> IT DOESN'T HAPPEN OFTEN SO I
VERY MUCH APPRECIATE YOU ALSO THANK YOU TO OUR COMMUNITY
MEMBERS AND LEADERS. YOU'RE ALL OUT HERE FOR YOUR
CONTINUED SUPPORT BUT MORE SPECIFICALLY FOR THE ENTIRE SAN
FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT AND THE OFFICERS, MANY OF THEM
WHO ARE HERE WITH US TODAY. I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR ALL THE
WORK THAT YOU'RE DOING TO MAKE SAN FRANCISCO SAFE AND GRATEFUL
. >> I ALSO WANT TO THANK OUR
S.F. PD COMMAND STAFF WHO ARE ALSO HERE INCLUDING CHIEF
DERRICK LU AND ASSISTANT CHIEF NICOLE JONES.
>> IT HAS BEEN AN ABSOLUTE PRIVILEGE TO WORK ALONGSIDE
THIS COMMAND STAFF AND OUR S.F. PD OFFICERS THROUGHOUT MY
POLICE CAREER THE LAST SIX MONTHS SERVING AS INTERIM CHIEF
OF POLICE WAS AN HONOR OF A LIFETIME.
THANK YOU MAYOR DANIEL LEARY FOR YOUR FOR TRUSTING ME TO
LEAD THE FINEST AND GREATEST POLICE DEPARTMENT IN THE
NATION. >> THANK YOU.
I WANT TO TAKE A MOMENT TO REFLECT ON THE WORK AND SOME OF
THE ACCOMPLISHMENTS OF OUR DEPARTMENT AND OF OUR OFFICERS.
>> SAN FRANCISCO'S HISTORIC LOW CRIME RATE AT 25 TO 30%
DECREASE IS A DIRECT RESULT OF OUR POLICE OFFICERS HARD WORK
AS THEY CONSISTENTLY PREVENT AND INVESTIGATE CRIMES, PROTECT
OUR COMMUNITIES AND HOLD CRIMINALS ACCOUNTABLE.
>> WE OPENED A NEW REAL TIME INVESTIGATION CENTER OR ARCTIC
TO DEPLOY TECHNOLOGIES LIKE DRONES TO SUPPORT THE WORK
AND EFFORTS OF OUR FRONTLINE POLICE OFFICERS TRACKING
CRIMINALS WHO COME TO SAN FRANCISCO TO COMMIT CRIMES LIKE
RETAIL THEFT AND CAR BREAK INS. I AM TRULY GRATEFUL AND PROUD
OF ALL OUR OFFICERS AND THE COMMITMENT THEIR COMMITMENT TO
SERVING OUR COMMUNITIES IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU. >> I AM ALSO GRATEFUL FOR THE
STRENGTHENED PARTNERSHIPS WITH OUR LOCAL, STATE AND FEDERAL
PUBLIC SAFETY PARTNERS TO COMBAT OPEN AIR DRUG, ILLEGAL
DRUG SALES AND DRUG USE AND FUGITIVE RECOVERY IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> THESE OPERATIONS WOULD NOT
HAVE BEEN POSSIBLE WITHOUT THE HELP FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO
SHERIFF'S OFFICE. >> THANK YOU, SHERIFF PAUL
MIYAMOTO, THE DISTRICT ATTORNEY'S OFFICE.
THANK YOU, BROOKE JENKINS. THE DEA, THE FBI, THE UNITED
STATES DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE AND THE U.S. ATTORNEY'S OFFICE
. THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE
DEPARTMENT HAS INTENSIFIED OPERATIONS AROUND DRUG
ENFORCEMENT. OUR FEDERAL PARTNERS HAVE ALSO
INCREASED THEIR OWN OPERATIONS TO SUPPORT OUR SHARED GOAL OF
KEEPING SAN FRANCISCO SAFE. JUST LAST YEAR ALONE, THE DRUG
MARKETING COORDINATION CENTER OR DEMATIC SEIZED 56 POUNDS OF
FENTANYL WHILE OFFICERS MADE OVER 6600 ARRESTS RELATED TO
DRUG ACTIVITY. >> COLLECTIVELY OUR MESSAGE IS
CLEAR ANYONE SELLING OR USING ILLEGAL DRUGS IN SAN FRANCISCO
WILL BE ARRESTED. POLICE OFFICERS WILL CONTINUE
THIS EFFORT FOR AS LONG AS IT TAKES.
WE NEED MORE POLICE OFFICERS IN OUR COMMUNITIES AND WE'VE
BEEN DOING SOME WORK ON RECRUITMENT.
YES, WE ARE HIRING. >> THIS PAST YEAR MARKED THE
FIRST NET POSITIVE IN OFFICERS PATROLLING THE STREETS
AND NEIGHBORHOODS FOR THE FIRST TIME SINCE THE 2020 GLOBAL
PANDEMIC. >> THE SPEEDY ACADEMY HAS HAD
FOUR FULL CLASSES IN A ROW WITH THE NEWEST ACADEMY CLASS
STARTING LAST MONTH. >> WHAT IS ENCOURAGING IS THAT
WE ARE SEEING MORE HIGH QUALITY APPLICANTS DUE TO OUR WORK ON
STREAMLINING, STREAMLINING THE HIRING PROCESS AND INCREASING
OUTREACH AND ADVERTISING FOR BOTH ENTRY LEVEL AND LATERAL
POLICE OFFICERS. >> MORALE AMONG POLICE OFFICERS
IS HIGHER AS WE CONTINUE TO FOCUS OUR EFFORTS ON PROVIDING
BACK BEAT BACK TO BASICS POLICE SERVICES.
THAT IS WHAT POLICE OFFICERS DO BEST KEEPING OUR STREETS CLEAN
AND SAFE. FOR THOSE WHO LIVE, WORK
AND PLAY IN SAN FRANCISCO, I WILL CLOSE WITH THIS WITH CHIEF
DERRICK LIEU AND HIS COMMAND STAFF NOW LEADING THE SAN
FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT. >> OUR MISSION OF KEEPING THE
CITY SAFE WITH INTEGRITY AND RESPECT WILL CONTINUE TO
FLOURISH, GROW AND THRIVE. THANK YOU AGAIN.
SAN FRANCISCO RESIDENTS MAYOR DANIEL MURRAY FOR THE
OPPORTUNITY TO SERVE SAN FRANCISCO AS CHIEF OF POLICE.
THANK YOU TO ALL THE S.F. PD OFFICERS FOR YOUR COMMITMENT TO
SERVE, PROTECT AND ENGAGE OUR COMMUNITIES.
>> I AM PROUD OF ALL OF YOU. WE ARE ALL BACK THERE.
THANK YOU FOR THAT. >> STAY SENDING THANK YOU TO
ALL THE COMMUNITY MEMBERS AND LEADERS ALL OF YOU OUT HERE
WHO HAVE CONTINUED TO SUPPORT THIS DEPARTMENT AND ALL OUR
OFFICERS. >> THIS IS FOR YOU.
>> SORRY, MAYOR. I'M GOING TO STEAL A LINE FROM
YOU. LET'S GO SAN FRANCISCO
AND LET'S GO S.F. PD. THANK YOU, CHIEF.
YET? IF YOU AND THE MAYOR WOULD LIKE
TO JOIN US IN THE WELL, WHERE'S MY DONUTS AND DO WE WANT TO
HAVE THE D.A. JOIN AS WELL IN THE SHERIFF?
JOIN YOU? I LOVE ONE MORE ONE GREAT.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY, I BET YOUR STAFF WOULD LOVE TO DO A A
LARGE GROUP PORCH GROUP PICTURE OUT IN THE ROTUNDA IS MY GUESS
AND YOU SHOULD BE HERE FOR MY COMMENDATION.
>> BUT I WILL EXCUSE YOU. >> I UNDERSTAND THAT BECAUSE
WHAT THIS MEANS FOR ME IS THAT SORT OF PUTS OUR GUARD AGAINST
SOME VICTIMS HERE BUT EASIER FOR OH MY GOD.
NOW IT'S TAKEN A WHILE TO NOW NET CHIEF YET IF YOU DO THE
HANDSHAKES OUT IN THE HALLWAY THAT WILL ALLOW PEOPLE TO LEAVE
THE CHAMBER. YEAH.
OKAY. YOU YEAH RIGHT I AND YOU'RE NOT
UP YET. OH ALL RIGHT SO BRIAN DOYLE IS
GOING TO GET THAT DOOR CLOSED. CAN YOU HELP HIM CLOSE THE DOOR
. AND AS WE PREPARE FOR THE
DISTRICT EIGHT COMMENDATION I WOULD NOTE THAT WE HAVE BEEN
JOINED BY CURRENT CITY TREASURER JOSE CISNEROS.
THANKS FOR JOINING US. GOOD TO SEE YOU.
ALL RIGHT. SO I WOULD LIKE TO INVITE THE
COMMUNITY PARTNER NETWORK ADVISORY COMMITTEE TO COME ON
UP. >> ILDIKO RESCH, SHE IRMA
JOLINE KATH MATTHEW MIKAYLA COLLEAGUES AND I SUSPECT SOME
OF YOU MIGHT WANT TO SAY SOME THINGS TO ABOUT THIS GROUP AS
WELL. TODAY I'M RECOGNIZING SEVEN SAN
FRANCISCANS WHO STEPPED UP TO HELP WRITE THE GREAT WRONG DONE
TO SO MANY COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS BY THE
MISMANAGEMENT AND ULTIMATE DISSOLUTION OF THE PARKS
ALLIANCE. >> AND THEY ARE ILDIKO POLONI
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE SUTRO STEWARDS PRESS.
RASHID ZARIF, PRESIDENT OF THE BUENA VISTA NEIGHBORHOOD
ASSOCIATION AND IRMA LEWIS, PRESIDENT OF THE FRIENDS OF A
FREE PARK JOLEEN YEE OF THE FRIENDS OF FRANKLIN SQUARE.
KATH SOKOLOFF OF FRIENDS OF LAKESIDE VILLAGE.
>> MATTHEW BLAIN CHAIR OF THE S.F. URBAN RIDERS AND MAKAYLA
DUDLEY, CHIEF OF STAFF OF THIRD PLATEAU.
>> NOW IT'S MY UNDERSTANDING THAT EIGHT MONTHS AGO THESE
PEOPLE DID NOT KNOW EACH OTHER. TODAY WITH A LITTLE BIT OF
ASSISTANCE FROM CITY HALL CITY HALL BUT A WHOLE LOT OF HELP
FROM VERY GENEROUS PRIVATE DONORS.
>> THEY HAVE DONE SOMETHING EXTRAORDINARY LAST SPRING AS
EVERYONE ON THIS BOARD KNOWS ALL TOO WELL THE PARKS ALLIANCE
COLLAPSED AFTER YEARS OF FINANCIAL MISMANAGEMENT.
PROJECTS STOPPED OVERNIGHT. NEARLY 90 COMMUNITY GROUPS
ORGANIZATIONS THAT MAINTAIN OUR TRAILS, RESTORE OUR PLAYGROUNDS
AND CARE FOR OUR OPEN SPACES WERE SUDDENLY LEFT WITHOUT THE
FUNDS THAT HAD BEEN RAISED AND ENTRUSTED TO THE PARKS
ALLIANCE. SMALL BUSINESSES WENT UNPAID
VOLUNTEERS WHO HAD ALREADY SPENT THEIR OWN MONEY TO FINISH
PROJECTS HAD NO IDEA WHETHER THEY WOULD EVER BE REIMBURSED.
I AM PRETTY SURE THAT EACH OF US HAS STORIES FROM OUR OWN
DISTRICTS TO THIS EFFECT. AND OF COURSE THIS WAS NOT JUST
A BETRAYAL OF CITY HALL. THIS WAS A BETRAYAL OF REGULAR
SAN FRANCISCANS THE PEOPLE WHO EVERY DAY TAKE IT UPON
THEMSELVES TO MAKE THE CITY BETTER IN WAYS ONE MIGHT EXPECT
THE LOCAL GOVERNMENT TO DO. BUT FOR A VARIETY OF REASONS IT
DOES NOT. >> BUT AS THAT STAR SORRY STORY
WAS PLAYING OUT, TWO OTHER MORE HOPEFUL THINGS WERE HAPPENING
ON PARALLEL TRACKS ON ONE TRACK.
THE LEADERS OF IMPACTED ORGANIZATIONS BEGAN FINDING
EACH OTHER AND STRATEGIZING ABOUT HOW TO MAKE THEIR
ORGANIZATIONS WHOLE AND MAYBE EVEN COME OUT OF THIS DISASTER
STRONGER ON THE OTHER SIDE. >> ILDIKO POLONI OF THE SUTRA
STEWARDS AND RASHID ZARIF OF ONE OF US TWO NEIGHBORHOOD
ASSOCIATION WERE THERE AT THE BEGINNING OF THIS ORGANIZING
EFFORT. TOO LATE TWO LEADERS BECAME SIX
AND SOON A BROADER GROUP CAME TOGETHER WITH A SHARED PURPOSE
RESTORING WHAT HAD BEEN LOST AND PROTECTING THE FUTURE OF
THEIR WORK. THIS GRASSROOTS EFFORT BECAME
WHAT WE NOW KNOW AS THE COMMUNITY PARTNER NETWORK.
>> NOW AT THE SAME TIME SUSAN HIRSCH OF THIRD PLATEAU WAS
HIDING BACK THERE IN THE AUDIENCE BECAUSE SHE DOESN'T
LIKE BEING ACKNOWLEDGED AND IS NOW BEING EMBARRASSED BY IT BUT
BY PRESIDENT MANDELBAUM BEGAN TO EXPLORE THE POSSIBILITY OF
RAISING PRIVATE PHILANTHROPIC DOLLARS TO MAKE THE COMMUNITY
ORGANIZATIONS WHOLE. >> SHE REACHED OUT AS WELL TO
THE MAYOR'S OFFICE AND ME AND OTHERS AS SHE WORKED TO
IDENTIFY FUNDING SOLUTIONS AND A PATH FORWARD FOR GETTING
COMMUNITY GROUPS PAID. >> EVENTUALLY THE MAYOR'S
OFFICE SORT OF MERGED THESE TWO CONVERSATIONS.
BY JUNE, STACY SLAUGHTER AND ALISHA JOHN BAPTISTE
AND SUSAN HIRSCH SAT DOWN WITH THIS GROUP THE COMMUNITY
PARTNER NETWORK ADVISORY COUNCIL TO CONSIDER A PATH
FORWARD. >> ENTER MAKAYLA DUDLEY, CHIEF
OF STAFF AT THIRD PLATEAU TOGETHER WITH SUSAN AND THE
LEADERS OF THE COMMUNITY PARTNER NETWORK.
THEY WORK DAY AND NIGHT TO SECURE THE NEEDED FUNDING.
ULTIMATELY THEY IDENTIFIED NEARLY 50 DONORS AND RAISED
MORE THAN $2 MILLION TO COVER WHAT THE PARKS ALLIANCE HAD
MISSPENT. >> A FEW ARE A FEW
ORGANIZATIONS AND INDIVIDUALS DESERVE A SPECIAL SHOUT OUT.
BAKER STREET FOUNDATION KRANK START THE POWER STATION
FOUNDATION. THANK YOU.
ENRIQUE LANDER, RANDI AND BOB FISHER.
AND I THINK RANDY'S HERE. THE JOHN PRITZKER FAMILY FUND,
SUE AND DAVID TUNNEL ALL GAVE VERY GENEROUSLY.
OUR OWN REC PARK COMMISSIONER HERE, KAT ANDERSON CONTRIBUTED
TO THE EFFORT. THE GENEROSITY OF THE FOLKS WHO
CONTRIBUTED TO THIS IS NOTABLE IN THAT MANY OF THESE
INDIVIDUALS AND ORGANIZATIONS HAD THEMSELVES BEEN VICTIMS OF
PARKS ALLIANCE MALFEASANCE CONTINUE TO IMPACT LED BY THEIR
PROGRAM DIRECTOR AMANDA PLACENTIA STEPPED UP AS A
FISCAL SPONSOR TO HELP MANAGE AND DISTRIBUTE THE DONATED
DOLLARS AND ROB WECHSLER, SENIOR COUNSEL AT ADLER
AND COLVIN ENSURED THAT EVERYTHING WAS DONE BY THE
BOOK. THE SAN FRANCISCO NEIGHBORHOOD
AND PARKS FUND OPENED FOR APPLICATIONS IN MID-SEPTEMBER
AND BY MID-NOVEMBER HAD IDENTIFIED ALL ELIGIBLE
RECIPIENTS ACROSS THE CITY BY THE END OF DECEMBER THE MONEY
WAS SUCCESSFULLY DISTRIBUTED TO THE ORGANIZATIONS WHO WERE OWED
IT AND SO IT SEEMED APPROPRIATE HERE AS WE START 2020, 2026 TO
ACKNOWLEDGE THIS MILESTONE AND THANK THIS GROUP OF PEOPLE
WHO HELPED US GET HERE. OUR HONOREES ILDIKO OR CHIC
IRMA, JOLENE, KATHE, MATTHEW AND MIKAYLA THE TALES OF THE
PARKS ALLIANCE IS TRULY A DISPIRITING ONE BUT THE TALE OF
THE COMMUNITY PARTNER NETWORK GIVES US HOPE.
>> THESE LEADERS AND THEIR PARTNERS IN THE PHILANTHROPIC
SECTOR TURNED A WORST POSSIBLE SCENARIO INTO A BLUE HELLO INTO
A BLUEPRINT FOR WHAT'S POSSIBLE WHEN EVERY DAY BUT
EXTRAORDINARY SAN FRANCISCANS WORK TOGETHER TO MAKE A BETTER
FUTURE FOR US ALL. WHAT WERE PREVIOUSLY 90 PLUS
COMMUNITY GROUPS WORKING INDEPENDENTLY ACROSS SAN
FRANCISCO ARE NOW A COLLABORATIVE MODEL FOR
STEWARDSHIP OF SAN FRANCISCO'S PARKS AND OPEN SPACES FOR
GENERATIONS TO COME. AND SO I WANT TO INVITE I THINK
I'M INVITING ILDIKO AND RASHI OR RASHICA AND ILDIKO OR ANY OF
YOU TO COME FORWARD AND SAY A FEW WORDS.
BUT BUT YOU KNOW WHAT? BEFORE YOU'RE ABLE TO DO THAT I
WAS RIGHT THAT MY COLLEAGUES WOULD WANT TO SAY SOME THINGS.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL WELL THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANTEL AND THANK
YOU FOR FOR COMMENDING THIS EFFORT.
THESE VOLUNTEERS, THE WHOLE COHORT OF SUPPORTERS.
YOU KNOW, WHEN I THINK ALL OF US MOST OF US SAT IN THESE
CHAMBERS IN A FAIRLY BEWILDERING SESSION SEVERAL
MONTHS AGO, IT PROBABLY WOULD HAVE BEEN EASY TO GO HOME
AND CRY. AND MAYBE WE DID.
BUT YOU ALSO STEPPED UP AND GOT ORGANIZED AND TOOK ACTION
AND THAT IS JUST SUCH A GREAT EXAMPLE FOR THIS CITY.
NOW OF YOU ALL. I WILL BE HONEST I KNOW CATH
THE BEST. AND THE FACT THAT YOU ALL ARE
PEOPLE THAT KATH WANTS TO STAND NEXT TO MEANS THAT YOU MUST BE
ABSOLUTELY STELLAR. SO I WANT TO COMMEND ALL OF YOU
FOR THAT BECAUSE I THINK THE WORLD OF KATH AND SO FOR YOU
ALL THANK YOU. YOU KNOW IN DISTRICT TWO YOU
KNOW WE'RE VERY LUCKY TO HAVE FRIENDS OF LAFAYETTE PARK ALL
AT THE PLAZA PARK FRANCISCO PARK CONSERVANCY AND THEY'VE
GOT GREAT LEADERS ANITA DEN STEFAN FRANZ, MARC MEYER
AND AND I WORK MOST CLOSELY WITH THEM.
BUT YOU ALL MAKE THIS CITY GREAT.
YOUR DEDICATION DOES AND IN ALL THIS THERE ALSO YOU KNOW, IT
SHOWED THAT THE CITY CAME TOGETHER.
YOU KNOW, SUSAN, THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP.
HAPPY I SEE YOU OUT THERE. YEAH YEAH I KNOW RANDY THAT'S
YOU I'M TALKING ABOUT YOU HAPPY I SEE YOU OUT THERE.
NO. YEAH.
I THANK YOU FOR YOUR FRIENDSHIP AND LEADERSHIP AND YOU KNOW, I
THINK WHAT'S GREAT IS THAT, YOU KNOW KAT ANDERSON, THE
PRESIDENT OF PARKS COMMISSION GOT PAST COMMISSIONERS INVOLVED
AND KAT AND CARRIE WYNN TROBE WHO I HAPPEN TO THINK MIGHT BE
HERE. THANK YOU FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP
IN STEPPING UP AND MAKING THIS COMMUNITY EFFORT AS WELL.
BUT TO YOU ALL THANK YOU FOR YOUR STEWARDSHIP, FOR YOUR
LEADERSHIP AND PROVIDING AN EXAMPLE OF HOW WE CAN GET OUR
HANDS DIRTY TO MAKE THINGS BETTER.
THANKS, ROSIE. CHERYL SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK
YOU PRESIDENT, FOR THIS RECOGNITION OF THESE WONDERFUL
PEOPLE. I THINK THIS EFFORT IS THE
LOVECHILD OF, YOU KNOW, COMP TERMS AND LEADERSHIP.
>> AND I'M REALLY GRATEFUL THAT AFTER ALL OF THOSE AGONIZING
CONVERSATIONS THAT I HAD WITH SO MANY PEOPLE IN DISTRICT
SEVEN INCLUDING ILDIKO AND KATHY AND THE DETROIT
PEOPLE IN ANY NUMBER OF ORGANIZATIONS THAT HAD FOR
YEARS BEEN WORKING REALLY HARD TO LOVE OUR CITY AND TO RAISE
FUNDS AND TO DO THE HARD WORK AT TO MEET OUR COLLECTIVE GOALS
AFTER THE IMPLOSION OF THE PARKS ALLIANCE, YOU KNOW, WE
HAD ALL THOSE REALLY DIFFICULT CONVERSATIONS.
I THINK IT WAS LIKE THE FIRST CONVERSATION I HAD WITH ALEESHA
JOHN BAPTIST WHEN SHE FIRST CAME ON BOARD AND SO I AM
NUMBER ONE REALLY GRATEFUL TO THIS MAYOR FOR TAKING IT
SERIOUSLY. LEE.
AND I'M REALLY GRATEFUL TO SUSAN HIRSCH FOR YOU KNOW, THAT
JUST BIG LIFT OF CONNECTING PEOPLE, CONNECTING DONORS
AND PROVIDING A FRAMEWORK. >> BUT I ALSO I'M SO GRATEFUL
FOR ALL OF YOU BECAUSE IT TAKES A LOT OF FAITH NOT JUST IN THE
PROCESS BUT IN EACH OTHER AND IN COMMUNITY TO LIKE STEP
OUTSIDE THE COMFORT ZONE AND SAY OKAY WE'RE GOING TO
BUILD SOMETHING NEW AND IT'S GOING TO WORK AS IT HAS TO INTO
YOU KNOW, CREATE SOMETHING NEW AND WONDERFUL OUT OF IT.
SO THANK YOU FOR THE RECOGNITION.
PRESIDENT WELL-DESERVED. I'M GRATEFUL FOR ALL OF YOU
AND FOR YOUR HARD WORK AND THAT WE HAVE YOU TO THANK FOR HAVING
A FUTURE IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR ALL OF THESE WONDERFUL PROJECTS
AND ALL THE WORK THAT WE'RE TRYING TO COLLECTIVELY DO
TOGETHER. >> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR WALTON
THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MERRIMAN. I JUST WANT TO FIRST OF ALL
JUST TAKE THE TIME TO THANK EACH AND EVERY ONE OF YOU FOR
YOUR ADVOCACY NOT ONLY ON BEHALF OF SOME OF YOUR OWN
ORGANIZATIONS BUT FOR ALL THE ORGANIZATIONS THAT HAD TO
SUFFER BECAUSE OF THE TRAGEDY THAT WAS THE PARKS ALLIANCE AT
THE TIME YOU ALL STEPPED UP THROUGH HEARINGS, THROUGH MANY
CONVERSATIONS AND BROUGHT COMMUNITY TOGETHER DURING THIS
PROCESS AND SO WANT TO APPRECIATE EACH AND EVERY ONE
OF YOU FOR THAT. THIS WAS SOMETHING THAT COULD
IT TURNED OUT DIFFERENTLY AND IT WAS A DISASTER FOR A LOT
OF A LOT OF ORGANIZATIONS AND A LOT OF COMMUNITY.
AND SO ALL OF YOU WORKING TOGETHER WITH SOME OF OUR FOLKS
IN THE PRIVATE SECTOR AND SOME OF OUR FOLKS IN COMMUNITY THAT
UNDERSTOOD THE MAGNITUDE OF HOW COMMUNITIES AND NEIGHBORHOODS
WERE AFFECTED. THIS IS SOMETHING JUST TO SAY
THAT THIS IS WHAT SAN FRANCISCO IS AND SHOULD BE ABOUT
AND PEOPLE SHOULD COME TOGETHER WHEN WE HAVE ISSUES LIKE THIS
IN OUR CITY. SO I WANT TO THANK ALL OF YOU
FOR TAKING THAT BIG STEP AND COMING TOGETHER TO LOOK OUT
FOR THE REST OF THE COMMUNITIES ALL ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU. YOU AS WELL.
I DID. I SEE ANOTHER SUPERVISOR IN THE
QUEUE OR MAYBE NOT. OKAY.
WELL WITH THAT THEN WE WILL INVITE I GUESS BUILD A CO
BUILDING UP. HELLO.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MANDEL. MAN THANK YOU EVERYBODY IN THE
CHAMBER. THANK YOU ALL THE SUPERVISORS.
>> THANK YOU EVERYONE FOR COMING.
MY NAME IS ELDER COPPOLA AND I'M THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR
OF SUTRO STEWARDS. >> IT'S THE NEW YEAR JANUARY
FIRST JUST HAPPENED AND YOU KNOW, USUALLY I DO NEW YEAR'S
RESOLUTIONS THIS YEAR I WAS LIKE LAID OUT FLAT WITH
EXHAUSTION AND AND REALLY FEEL THE NEED TO LIKE STEP BACK
AND THINK ABOUT WHAT'S HAPPENED.
AND I THINK OVERALL THE TAKEAWAY FOR ME IS ECHOING A
LOT OF WHAT PEOPLE HAVE SAID. BUT I THINK WHAT WAS UNUSUAL
AND AND INCREDIBLE WAS THE WAY THAT WE DID ALL COME TOGETHER.
SO NOT JUST THE SEVEN OF US HERE BUT ALSO EVERYONE IN THIS
ROOM, ALL THE COMMUNITY PARTNERS, THE CITY GOVERNMENT,
CITY AGENCIES, FUNDERS, THE MAYOR'S OFFICE AND REALLY THE
QUESTION WASN'T WHODUNIT WRINGING OUR HANDS WITH THE
BLAME GAME BUT HOW CAN WE PREVENT FUTURE HARM AND HOW CAN
WE MINIMIZE THE HARM BECAUSE ALREADY HARM HAS BEEN DONE.
WHEN I FIRST SAW THAT NEWSPAPER ARTICLE FROM THE CHRONICLE ON
APRIL 28TH REALLY EXPOSING THE EXTENT OF THE PARKS ALLIANCE
DYSFUNCTION MY HEART LIKE FELL THROUGH THE ENTRAIN THAT I WAS
WRITING AT THE TIME AND I KNEW WITHIN WEEKS THAT NOT ONLY WERE
WE GOING TO LOSE ALL OUR MONEY BUT WE WERE GOING TO LOSE OUR
FISCAL SPONSOR AND THAT'S EXACTLY WHAT HAPPENED.
>> SO THE QUESTION BECAME WHEN RASHICA AND I MET AND ALSO HE'S
INCREDIBLE. >> THANK YOU SO, SO MUCH.
>> SO WHEN WE MET THE QUESTION REALLY WAS HOW DO WE GET OUR
MONEY BACK BECAUSE THIS IS ABSOLUTELY UNACCEPTABLE
AND ALSO WHERE ARE WE GOING TO LAND?
>> WHAT IS OUR FISCAL HOME GOING TO BE?
SO WITH EVERYONE COMING TOGETHER TODAY HERE WE STAND
WITH OVER 8080 COMMUNITY GROUPS WHO HAVE RECEIVED MORE THAN 80%
OF THEIR MONEY BACK THANKS TO EFFORTS BY SUSAN HIRSCH AND ALL
THE WONDERFUL DONORS IN THIS ROOM AND BEYOND, MOST OF US
HAVE FOUND FISCAL HOMES THE FISCAL SPONSORS DESERVE A HUGE
THANKS. >> THESE ARE GROUPS THAT YOU
KNOW, MANY OF WHOM WERE UNDERSTAFFED AND REALLY ROSE TO
THE CHALLENGE. >> SO LIKE INDEPENDENT ARTS
AND MEDIA A LIVABLE CITY COMMUNITY INITIATIVES I'M SURE
THERE'S OTHERS THAT I'M NOT THAT I'M NOT REMEMBERING RIGHT
NOW BUT BUT MANY FISCAL SPONSORS WHO EVEN CREATED LIKE
AD HOC AGREEMENTS IN THE INTERIM AND A TEMPORARY
SITUATION LIKE PEOPLE REALLY JUST FIGURED OUT HOW CAN WE
MAKE THIS WORK? >> AND I THINK THAT'S THAT'S
TOO OFTEN FORGOTTEN. >> AND REALLY WHAT IT TAKES IS
LIKE WHAT ARE THE CREATIVE MECHANISMS IF THE GOAL IS X,
HOW THE F DO WE GET THERE? AND WE FIGURED IT OUT SO STILL
THERE ARE COMMUNITY PARTNERS WHO DON'T HAVE FISCAL HOMES YET
AND WE'RE NOT ABANDONING EACH OTHER.
WE'RE COMING TOGETHER. WE FORMED A COLLECTIVE TO
CONTINUE TO SUPPORT EACH OTHER SO THIS STORY HAS THE POTENTIAL
TO TO CONTINUE ITS POSITIVE MOMENTUM AND I THINK THAT'S
SOMETHING THAT WE CAN ALL TAKE AWAY FROM THIS IS THAT WHEN WE
COME TOGETHER AND WE AND WE SORT OF DO AWAY WITH WITH
TYPICAL BOUNDARIES BETWEEN CITY GOVERNMENT AND NEIGHBOR
AND COMMUNITY MEMBER AND CITY AGENCY AND FUNDER AND DOG
WALKER THAT THAT WE REALLY CAN DO AMAZING THINGS.
>> AND WHEN I LOOK AT WHERE WE ARE SITTING IN THE YEAR 2026 WE
WE GOT TO DO THAT GUYS LIKE THERE'S A LOT OF REALLY CRAZY
STUFF HAPPENING IN THIS CITY AND AND THEN THIS COUNTRY SO WE
I THINK LET'S TAKE THIS MOMENTUM AND CONTINUE WITH IT
JUST TREMENDOUS GRATITUDE TO EVERYONE HERE AND I REALLY SEE
THIS AS AS A COMMENDATION NOT FOR ONLY THE THE SEVEN OF US
BUT BUT FOR ALL THE COMMUNITY PARTNERS WE WOULDN'T HAVE BEEN
ABLE TO RAISE THE MONEY IF IT WEREN'T FOR THE WORK THE
COMMUNITY PARTNERS HAVE BEEN DOING FOR DECADES.
SO IF ANY OF YOU WANT TO STAND UP WHO AREN'T HERE RIGHT NOW,
WHO AREN'T STANDING HERE BUT WHO DO REPRESENT A COMMUNITY
PARTNER I KNOW THERE'S OTHERS OF YOU IN THE ROOM ARE THERE
NOT? YOU'RE SHY.
OKAY. WELL I SEE THIS AS A AS AN
AWARD FOR THEM AS WELL. IF IT WEREN'T FOR THEIR WORK,
YOU KNOW, NO ONE WOULD HAVE TAKEN THIS AS SERIOUSLY AS THEY
ENDED UP DOING. >> SO THANK YOU, RASHID.
AND KEEP RAFFA YOU'RE GOING TO GIVE ME TWO MINUTES OR YES AS I
SAY AS MUCH TIME AS YOU WANT BUT DISTRICT EIGHT'S OWN RASHID
ZARIF. >> THANK YOU, RAFAEL.
THANK YOU ALL TO GO FOR THAT ACCEPTANCE SPEECH AS WELL AS
THANK YOU ALL FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
IT'S BEEN IT'S REALLY APPRECIATIVE TO BE RECOGNIZED
FOR WHAT WE'VE DONE BUT IT'S REALLY IMPORTANT TO NOTE THAT
WE DIDN'T DO THIS ALONE. >> I DO WANT TO RECOGNIZE THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND THE MAYOR'S OFFICE FOR DOING YOUR
PART. IT WAS VERY EYE OPENING ON WHAT
YOU'VE DONE BEHIND THE SCENES LISTENING AND SUPPORTING YOUR
CONSTITUENTS. YOU STEPPED IN TO BRING THE
RIGHT STAKEHOLDERS TOGETHER. THANK YOU SUSAN FOR EVERYTHING
YOU'VE DONE THROUGH THIS CONNECTION YOU PUBLICLY
ELEVATED THE NEED FOR ACCOUNTABILITY AND THAT WAS
JUST A SMALL PIECE OF THAT. >> SO WITH THAT WE THANK YOU TO
THE DONORS. WE RECOGNIZE YOU YOUR DONATION
NO MATTER HOW BIG OR SMALL SPOKE LOUDLY THAT THE WORK THAT
ALL OUR COMMUNITY GROUPS HAVE DONE MATTERS THAT WE ARE A
CRITICAL PART TO IMPROVING OUR CITY.
AND WITH THAT WE THANK YOU TO THE 90 PLUS COMMUNITY GROUPS
THAT HAVE SUFFERED THE PAST YEAR.
WE RECOGNIZE YOU. >> YOU'VE HAD TO PUT TRUST INTO
SEVEN RANDOM INDIVIDUALS THAT REALLY WE DID NOT KNOW EACH
OTHER. SOMEHOW IT ALL CAME TOGETHER
FROM DIFFERENT PARTS OF THE CITY TO REPRESENT THEM TOWARDS
AN UPHILL BATTLE THAT WAS THOUGHT IMPOSSIBLE TO ACHIEVE.
>> WE STUCK TOGETHER. >> WE WORKED TOGETHER AND WE
SUCCEEDED TOO. THAT SUCCEEDED TOGETHER.
>> AND WITH THAT WE THANK YOU TO THE FAMILIES OF THE ADVISORY
COMMITTEES ESPECIALLY MY WIFE AND KIDS THAT ARE BACK HERE.
WE RECOGNIZE YOU. >> YOU ENDURED MISSED DINNERS
OVER THE SUMMER, LATE NIGHT CALLS, COUNTLESS HOURS OF
FAMILY TIME SACRIFICED FOR THE BETTERMENT OF OUR CITY.
SO WITH THAT WE AND I MYSELF I THANK YOU.
>> HERE'S A SURPRISING PART OF THE ENTIRE EXPERIENCE IN THE
LAST EIGHT MONTHS WHILE WE STARTED WORKING WITH EACH OTHER
EIGHT EIGHT MONTHS AGO. >> THE MAJORITY OF US ARE JUST
MEETING EACH OTHER FOR THE FIRST TIME PHYSICALLY TODAY
THERE WAS NO PLAYBOOK IN WHAT WE DID.
THIS IS UNCHARTED WATERS PERSONALLY AND PROFESSIONALLY
BUT WE HAD A GOAL WE WERE STRIVING FOR.
WE HAD THE LOVE OF OUR CITY TO KEEP US GOING.
>> IMAGINE THE POSSIBILITIES IF JUST 5 OR 10 MORE NEW GROUPS
ARE FORMED NOT TO JUST POINT FINGERS AT YOU GUYS TO FIX CITY
PROBLEMS BUT TO WORK, TO PROBE, TO WORK TOGETHER AND POINTING
TOWARDS HOW TO SOLVE THEM TOGETHER.
THAT IS THE TRUE MAGIC OF THAT SAN FRANCISCANS CAN HARNESS.
>> THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU ALL AND I'LL COME
OUT THERE NOW SO THEY'RE COMING TO THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT WE'RE BEING MOVED. OKAY
. YEAH.
>> ALL RIGHT. LET'S GO BACK TO ROLL CALL OR
ACTUALLY NO, WE HAVE 3 P.M.. >> LET'S GO TO OUR 3 P.M.
SPECIAL ORDER, MADAM CLERK THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS SITTING AS A COMMITTEE OF THE
WHOLE SCHEDULING PURSUANT TO A RESOLUTION APPROVED ON DECEMBER
9TH ITEM 910 AND 11 ITEM NINE IS A PUBLIC HEARING OF THE
BOARD SITTING AS A COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE TODAY FOR TWO ITEMS
ITEM TEN WAS REFERRED WITHOUT RECOMMENDATION FROM THE LAND
USE AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE.
IT'S AN ORDINANCE TO ORDER THE VACATION OF PORTIONS OF HAWS
STREET GRIFFITHS STREET AND BANCROFT AVENUE FOR THE
DEVELOPMENT OF THE SAN FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT
TRAINING FACILITY AT 1236 CARROLL AVENUE TO PRESERVE
PUBLIC UTILITY AND ACCESS RIGHTS IN FAVOR OF THE CITY
AND EASEMENT RIGHTS FOR EXISTING ANY OVERHEAD
ELECTRICAL FACILITIES TO APPROVE THE INTERDEPARTMENTAL
TRANSFER OF THE STREET VACATION AREA FROM PUBLIC WORKS TO THE
FIRE DEPARTMENT TO AUTHORIZE OFFICIAL ACTS IN CONNECTION
WITH THE ORDINANCE AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION
AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
AND FOR ITEM 11 AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ZONING MAP OF THE
PLANNING CODE TO CHANGE THE ZONING USED DISTRICT
DESIGNATION OF ASSESSOR'S PARCEL BLOCK NUMBER 4877.
LOT NUMBERS 001 THROUGH 004 AND ASSESSOR'S PARCEL BLOCK
NUMBER 4852. LOT NUMBERS 002 THROUGH ZERO 22
THE FULL WIDTH OF BANCROFT AVENUE BETWEEN GRIFFITH STREET
AND GEORGE STREET AND THE FULL WIDTH OF GRIFFITH STREET
AND HORN STREET BETWEEN CARROLL AVENUE AND ARMSTRONG AVENUE.
COLLECTIVELY KNOWN AS 1236 CARROLL AVENUE FROM PDR TO
PRODUCTION DISTRIBUTION AND REPAIR DISTRICT TO END TO P
PUBLIC TO CHANGE THE HEIGHT AND BULK DISTRICT DESIGNATION
OF THE AFOREMENTIONED PARCELS AND ASSESSOR'S PARCEL BLOCK
NUMBER 4852. LOT NUMBER 001 FROM 40 DASH X
TO 90 DASH X AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION AND TO
MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
>> SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU PRESIDENT, MADAM AND COLLEAGUES
. THIS HEARING IS IN LINE WITH
TWO CRITICAL PIECES OF LEGISLATION ORDERING THE
VACATION OF PORTIONS OF HALL STREET GRIFFITH STREET
AND BANCROFT AVENUE TO FACILITATE THE DEVELOPMENT OF
THE SAN FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT'S NEW DIVISION OF
TRAINING FACILITY AT 1236 CARROLL AVENUE.
THIS PROJECT WILL CONSOLIDATE AND REPLACE OUTDATED TRAINING
FACILITIES CURRENTLY LOCATED ON TREASURE ISLAND AND IN THE
MISSION DISTRICT CREATING A MODERN STATE OF THE ART CAMPUS
FOR LIVE FIRE, CLASSROOM AND EQUIPMENT TRAINING AS WELL
AS URBAN SEARCH AND RESCUE SIMULATIONS.
THIS PROJECT HAS RECEIVED STRONG SUPPORT FROM THE BAYVIEW
HUNTERS POINT CITIZENS ADVISORY COMMITTEE AND WILL HAVE A
POSITIVE IMPACT ON THE BAY VIEW AND SURROUNDING COMMUNITY.
THIS IS VITAL. THIS IS A VITAL INVESTMENT
IN PUBLIC SAFETY AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT AND I URGE YOUR
SUPPORT FOR THESE IMPORTANT NEXT STEPS IN ADVANCING THE
FIRE DEPARTMENT'S TRAINING CAPABILITIES.
>> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT. THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR WALTON.
WE DO HAVE FIRE DEPARTMENT AND PUBLIC WORKS TO PRESENT
AND SO I WOULD INVITE INVITE FIRE TO START I GUESS.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON, PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN.
SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS GARRETT MILLER.
ASSISTANT DEPUTY CHIEF THE SAN FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT.
THANK YOU FOR CONSIDERING THIS MATTER.
IT WILL SUPPORT THE DEVELOPMENT OF A NEW SAN FRANCISCO FIRE
DEPARTMENT DEPARTMENT DIVISION OF TRAINING.
THE DIVISION OF TRAINING IS THE FOUNDATION OF THE SAN FRANCISCO
FIRE DEPARTMENT. ALL FIREFIGHTERS, EMTS
AND PARAMEDICS LEARN THEIR JOB SKILLS AT THE TOWER AS IT IS
KNOWN. THEY RETURN THROUGHOUT THEIR
CAREER FOR SKILLS MAINTENANCE UPDATES AND PROFESSIONAL
DEVELOPMENT. BUT MOST IMPORTANTLY THE
DIVISION OF TRAINING IS WHERE THE MISSION OF THE FIRE
DEPARTMENT AND THE COMMITMENT TO SERVICE IS INSTILLED
IN EVERY NEW CLASS. FOR ALMOST 160 YEARS THE SAN
FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT HAS BEEN PROTECTING LIVES
AND PROPERTY. IN THAT TIME THE ROLE OF THE
FIRE DEPARTMENT HAS GROWN AND INCREASED IN COMPLEXITY.
AND TODAY WE TRULY ARE AN ALL HAZARDS AGENCY.
OUR MEMBERS EXTINGUISH FIRES COMPLETE TECHNICAL AND WATER
RESCUES MITIGATE BEHAVIORAL CRISES, MEDICAL EMERGENCIES
AND HAZARDOUS MATERIALS INCIDENTS.
MOST OF THE TRAINING OCCURS AT THE FORMAL NAVAL FACILITY ON
TREASURE ISLAND WHICH IS PLANNED FOR DEMOLITION.
A NEW SFD DIVISION OF TRAINING IS TRULY ESSENTIAL TO OUR
DEPARTMENT AND OUR CITY AND I THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME
AND ATTENTION. >> PRESIDENT NEEDLEMAN
SUPERVISORS SCOTT MORAN FROM PUBLIC WORKS PROJECT MANAGER
GIVE YOU A QUICK OVERVIEW OF THE PROJECT AND THE
LEGISLATION. >> AS CHIEF MILLER HAD
EXPLAINED WITH THE CONSOLIDATION OF THE TWO
EXISTING TRAINING FACILITIES ONE ON TREASURE ISLAND WHICH
NEEDS TO BE VACATED AND THE OTHER WHICH IS QUITE ANTIQUATED
AT 19TH AND FOLSOM THOSE ARE TWO FACILITIES TO BE COMBINED
INTO A NEW LOCATION IN THE BAYVIEW DISTRICT.
>> THIS IS SHOWS A RENDERING OF THE SITE RELATIVE TO THE
SURROUNDING. IT'S ACTUALLY JUST NORTHWEST OF
THE ORIGINAL CANDLESTICK PARK AREA AND ACROSS THE BAY FROM
HUNTERS POINT. >> THE THE SITE IS SHOWN IN THE
CENTER IN RED AND IT'S ADJACENT TO THE CALIFORNIA STATE PARKS
LAND WHICH IS TO THE EAST. AND THEY PLAN TO EVENTUALLY
BUILD A STATE PARK VISITOR CENTER TO ACCESS THE BAY TRAIL
THAT WILL EVENTUALLY CONNECT HUNTERS POINT ALL THE WAY DOWN
TO CANDLESTICK POINT TO THE WEST IS A SITE OWNED BY
PROLOGIS WHICH HAS POTENTIAL TO EVENTUALLY BUILD A DISTRIBUTION
CENTER THAT WILL BE ABOUT 40FT TALL DIRECTLY ACROSS THE STREET
ON CARROLL IS THE NORTHWEST CORNER OF THE CANDLESTICK POINT
DEVELOPMENT WHICH IS THE LARGE MIXED USE REDEVELOPMENT AREA.
AND THEN THE OTHER AREAS TO THE NORTH AND TO THE WEST ARE
INDUSTRIAL. >> THIS SHOWS PLANNED
DEVELOPMENT FOR THE SITE. THE BUILDINGS THAT ARE
CONCENTRATED CLOSE TO CARROLL AVENUE ARE WHERE THE OCCUPIED
BUILDINGS WILL BE. THIS IS THE ADMINISTRATION
BUILDING THE CLASSROOMS AND SUPPORT STRUCTURES.
DIRECTLY TO THE NORTH ARE THE TRAINING BUILDINGS THESE ARE
UNOCCUPIED STRUCTURES THAT SIMULATE A VARIETY OF DIFFERENT
TYPES OF BUILDING STRUCTURES IN SAN FRANCISCO AND A VARIETY
OF RISKS FOR RESCUE AND FIRE OPERATIONS.
>> THE SITE WILL BE ENTIRELY ACCESSED FROM CARROLL AVENUE,
THE PRIMARY ENTRANCE BEING AT THE EAST SIDE ALIGNING WITH
WHAT WAS OR THE PAPER STREET OF GRIFFITH STREET.
AND THEN THERE'LL BE A SECONDARY SERVICE ENTRANCE ON
THE WEST SIDE ON WHAT WAS HALL STREET ON THE PAPER STREET.
THIS IS A RENDERING SHOWING THAT THE PLANNED BUILDOUT FOR
THE SITE AND ITS USES. THIS IS ANOTHER RENDERING KIND
OF SHOWING PERSPECTIVE LOOKING DOWN CARROLL AVENUE TOWARDS
WITH HUNTER'S POINT IN THE BACKGROUND.
THIS IS THE PRIMARY PUBLIC ENTRANCE AND THE MAIN VEHICULAR
ENTRANCE AND THE ENTRANCE AT THE STREET LEVEL FOR THE PUBLIC
. AND THIS IS A VIEW LOOKING DOWN
CARROLL TOWARDS THE WEST WITH THE PLANNED IMPROVEMENTS ON
CARROLL AVENUE. >> THE SITE ITSELF IS ACTUALLY
MADE UP OF 26 INDIVIDUAL PARCELS AND THREE PAPER STREETS
THAT WE HOPE TO VACATE THE ENTIRE SITE INCLUDING THE PAPER
STREETS IS JUST OVER EIGHT ACRES.
AND THE LEGISLATION HAS TWO COMPONENTS THE STREET VACATION
VACATING THE THREE STREETS THAT WE'RE TALKING ABOUT HALL
STREET, BANCROFT AND GRIFFITH STREET.
AND THEN THERE'S ALSO THE PLANNING CODE MAP AMENDMENTS
WHICH ARE A ZONING CHANGE AND A BULK HEIGHT CHANGE FOR STREET
VACATIONS. >> THIS RENDERING QUICKLY KIND
OF SHOWS YOU WHERE THOSE STREETS ARE.
THESE ARE PAPER STREETS THAT WERE PLAN BUT HAVE NEVER BEEN
BUILT. AND BASED ON WHERE THE BAY IS,
THESE STREETS REALLY WOULDN'T PROVIDE ANY ACCESS TO ANYTHING
THAT IS DEAD ENDS IN THAT AREA ANYWAY.
ALSO THE SITE ITSELF DROPS OFF SIGNIFICANTLY ON BOTH THE WEST
SIDE ON THE LEFT OF THE IMAGE HERE AND ALSO ON THE NORTH
SIDE, THE RIGHT SIDE OF THIS IMAGE UNDER THESE PAPER
STREETS. THERE ARE TWO PUC UTILITIES, A
SEWER MAIN THAT RUNS UNDERNEATH GRIFFITH'S STREET TO THE NORTH
AND CONNECTING TO ARMSTRONG. AND THEN ALSO A LARGE BOX SEWER
THAT RUNS UNDER BANCROFT AND UP HAWES.
IN ADDITION TO THAT THERE ARE ALSO SOME OVERHEAD POWER LINES
ON THE FAR WEST SIDE OF THE SITE WITHIN HAWES STREET THAT
FEED THAT BRING SUPPLY POWER TO THE TWO INDUSTRIAL BUILDINGS
DIRECTLY NORTH OF THE SITE. >> FOR THOSE UTILITIES THE
OVERHEAD POWER LINES THERE IS EASEMENT LANGUAGE EASEMENT
LANGUAGE THAT'S INCORPORATED INTO THE STREET VACATION
ORDINANCE FOR THE PUC BOX, SEWER AND SEWER MAIN.
THERE IS A MEMORANDUM OF UNDERSTANDING THAT HAS BEEN
SIGNED BETWEEN PUC AND THE FIRE DEPARTMENT, THE ADJACENT
LANDOWNERS THAT WOULD BE AFFECTED BY THE REMOVAL OF
THESE FUTURE STREETS. CALIFORNIA STATE PARKS ON THE
EAST SIDE WHICH ABUTS THE PAPER STREET OF GRIFFITH HAS GIVEN A
LETTER OF SUPPORT FOR THE VACATION ROAD AND THEN PRO-LAW
JUST ON THE WEST SIDE THAT ABUTS HAUSER STREET HAS ALSO
GIVEN A LETTER OF SUPPORT FOR THE PLANNING CODE MAP
AMENDMENTS. CURRENTLY THE SITE IS MADE UP
OF PDR TO OR PRODUCTION DISTRIBUTION REPAIR AND P
PUBLIC. AND THE PLAN IS TO CHANGE IT
ALL TO PUBLIC TO MATCH THE PLANNED USE AND TO BE
SUPPORTIVE THAT THE FIRE DEPARTMENTS USES IN THE FUTURE.
>> THE BULK HEIGHT CHANGE IS PRIMARILY DRIVEN BY THE FACT
THAT THERE ARE THE NEED FOR TRAINING STRUCTURES THAT NEED
TO BE TALL. ONE OF THEM IS IN THE CENTER OF
THE SITE AT THE TOP. >> IT'S A SIMULATED COMMUNITY
PATIENTS TOWER THAT IS USED FOR REC RESCUE SCENARIOS.
THE OTHER ONE IS A TRAINING TOWER THAT'S 84FT TALL AND IT
SIMULATES AN OFFICE BUILDING ON ONE SIDE OF IT AND A TALL
APARTMENT BUILDING ON THE OTHER SIDE OF IT.
>> THOSE STRUCTURES WERE PURPOSELY PLACED AS FAR AWAY
FROM THE RESIDENTS AS POSSIBLE TO AVOID IMPOSING STRUCTURES
AND ALSO TO KEEP THOSE TRAINING EXERCISES AWAY FROM THE
RESIDENTIAL AREAS. >> THOSE TWO STRUCTURES ARE
SHOWN IN THIS RENDERING AWAY FROM THE PLANNED FUTURE
DEVELOPMENT AROUND THIS AREA. >> THE NEXT PAGE HAS TWO
SECTIONS THAT SHOW THE RELATIVE HEIGHTS OF THE PLANNED
DEVELOPMENT AND THE SITE. LOOK THE FIRST ONE IS LOOKING
TO THE EAST DOWN CARROLL AVENUE AND SHOWS THE SITE WITH THOSE
TALL BUILDINGS ON THE FAR LEFT AND THE PLANNED FUTURE
DEVELOPMENT OF THE CANDLESTICK POINT ON THE RIGHT AT THE
BOTTOM SHOWS THE POTENTIAL FUTURE BUILDING BY PROLOGIS ON
THE LEFT AND THOSE TALL BUILDINGS IN THE DISTANCE.
AGAIN THOSE BUILDINGS ARE PURPOSELY SET BACK AWAY FROM
THE ROAD. >> COMMUNITY OUTREACH WE'VE
ACTUALLY DONE QUITE A BIT OF OUTREACH TO THE COMMUNITY
AND IN AUGUST THE BAYVIEW CITIZEN ADVISORY COMMITTEE
ACTUALLY VOTED UNANIMOUSLY TO RECOMMEND THAT THE PLANNING
COMMISSION APPROVE THE PLANNING CODE MAP AMENDMENTS.
>> AND THEN IN SUMMARY THE STREET THE LEGISLATION IS THE
STREET VACATIONS BANCROFT AVENUE FROM HALL STREET TO
GRIFFITH HALL STREET FROM CARROLL AVENUE TO ARMSTRONG
GRIFFITH STREET FROM CARROLL AVENUE TO ARMSTRONG.
AND THEN THE PLANNING CODE MAP AMENDMENTS ARE THE CHANGE
IN ZONING FROM PDR TO TWO PUBLIC AND THE BULK HEIGHT
CHANGE FROM 40 X TO 90 X. THE PLANNING CODE MAP
AMENDMENTS WERE RECOMMENDED FOR APPROVAL BY THE PLANNING
COMMISSION ON 1016 AND THEN ALSO RECOMMENDED BY THE LAND
USE AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE ON 12 EIGHT AND THAT
IS A SUMMARY. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR PRESENTATIONS.
I DO NOT SEE ANY OH I DO SEE A COLLEAGUE IN THE QUEUE.
>> SUPERVISOR JAN I THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDOM AND JUST WANT
TO THANK THE FIRE DEPARTMENT FOR THEIR WORK.
WE HAD THIS THERE WAS A FEDERAL GRANT FUNDING THAT ACTUALLY
CAME THROUGH THE BUDGET COMMITTEE TO CONTRIBUTE TO THE
TO CONTINUE TO FINISH THIS TRAINING FACILITY.
>> I WANT TO BE A CO-SPONSOR AND THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR
WALTON AND AMENDMENT FOR LEADING THE WAY WITH THIS
STREET VACATION. IT'S A NECESSARY STEP.
WE'D LIKE TO BE A CO-SPONSOR TO THE STREET VACATION AND JUST
REALLY CONTINUE TO EXPRESS MY SUPPORT FOR THE TRAINING
FACILITY THAT'S NOT ONLY BENEFITING SAN FRANCISCO BUT
REALLY FOR THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA.
AND AS WE CONTINUE TO FIGHT WILDFIRES, IT'S BEEN VERY
DIFFICULT. AND I JUST WANT TO JUST EXPRESS
THE GRATITUDE. IT'S ALWAYS DIFFICULT TO TRAIN
FIREFIGHTERS IN SCENARIOS AND HAVING A TRAINING FACILITY
IS CRITICAL NOT JUST FOR US BUT FOR THE STATE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR SUPERVISOR WALTON DID THE WORK ON THIS I THREW MY
NAME ON BECAUSE I VALUE THE WORK AND I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT
AS AS YOU DO SO WITH THAT LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT ON THIS
MATTER. THIS IS NOT GENERAL PUBLIC
COMMENT. THIS IS ITEMS NINE THROUGH 11
THAT WE'VE JUST HAD A PRESENTATION ON AND I DON'T SEE
ANYONE COMING FORWARD TO SPEAK ON THAT.
SO WE WILL CLOSE PUBLIC COMMENT ON THE ON THIS MATTER AND THEN
I THINK WE CAN SAY THAT THIS THIS MATTER HAS BEEN HEARD
AND IS NOW FILED AND WE WILL NOW CONSIDER ITEMS TEN AND 11.
MADAM LARK, I THINK CAN WE TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME HOUSE, SAME
CALL. YES, MR. PRESIDENT.
ALL RIGHT. WE'LL TAKE THESE ITEMS.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE ORDINANCES ARE
PASSED ON FIRST READING. ALL RIGHT.
NOW LET'S GO TO A ROLL CALL. >> YES, RESUMING ROLL CALL.
WE HAVE SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. >> COLLEAGUES ON DECEMBER 20TH
AS WE ARE ALL WELL AWARE, A FIRE AT PGE SUBSTATION PLUNGED
130,000 HOUSEHOLDS AND HUNDREDS OF TRAFFIC SIGNALS INTO
DARKNESS. >> THIS OUTAGE INTERFERED WITH
HOLIDAY SHOPPING, FOOD ACCESS AND THE SAFE OPERATION OF OUR
STREET NETWORK. >> THE SIGNIFICANT DISTURBANCE
DISTURBANCE IS WHY I COSPONSORED SUPERVISOR WONG'S
HEARING TO HOLD PGE ACCOUNTABLE.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WONG FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP.
>> HOWEVER, THE SITUATION ON OUR STREETS DURING THE OUTAGE
WAS EXACERBATED BY THE LARGE FLEET OF WAYMO AUTONOMOUS
VEHICLES WHICH STRUGGLED TO NAVIGATE THE DARK
AND UNCONTROLLED STREETS. >> THE CHRONICLE REPORTED THAT
DOZENS OF WAYMO'S CAME TO A HALT BLOCKING INTERSECTIONS
AND HOLDING UP TRAFFIC. >> AUTONOMOUS VEHICLES WERE
STRANDED AS THEY WAITED BEHIND TWO OTHER AVS AND HUMAN DRIVERS
AND PEDESTRIANS HAD TO MANEUVER AROUND THE STOPPED VEHICLES.
>> THERE WERE ALSO REPORTS OF WAYMO'S BLOCKING EMERGENCY
RESPONSE VEHICLES. >> THESE CHAOTIC SCENES COULD
BE SEEN ACROSS THE CITY UNTIL WAYMO PULLED ITS FLEET OFF THE
STREET FOR THE WEEKEND UNTIL POWER WAS RESTORED.
WHETHER FROM ELECTRICAL FIRES, A VIOLENT WINTER STORM OR A
PROTEST DOWNTOWN, THIS WON'T BE THE LAST TIME.
AUTONOMOUS VEHICLES WILL HAVE TO FACE SITUATIONS ON THE
STREET THAT ARE FAR FROM TYPICAL.
>> I BELIEVE AUTONOMOUS VEHICLES CAN PLAY A ROLE IN THE
FUTURE OF TRANSPORTATION. TO HELP REACH OUR VISION ZERO
GOALS BUT ONLY WHEN THESE COMPANIES OPERATE RESPONSIVE
PLAY. WE NEED TO KNOW WHAT WENT WRONG
WITH THESE VEHICLES, HOW THEY ARE PREPARING THEMSELVES TO
ENSURE THE NEXT DISASTER WON'T LEAD TO THE SAME CHAOS AS
WAYMO'S FLEET GROWS AND NEW AUTONOMOUS VEHICLE OPERATORS
COME TO SAN FRANCISCO, WE NEED TO KNOW THE CITY CAN WORK WITH
THEM ON OPERATING SAFELY IN EMERGENCIES.
>> IF THESE VEHICLES ARE TO SHARE THE ROADS WITH HUMAN
DRIVERS, PEDESTRIANS AND CYCLISTS THEY MUST BE ABLE
TO HANDLE HUMAN TRAFFIC DIRECTION AT INTERSECTIONS
TREATS SIGNAL SIGNALS INTERSECTIONS AS FOUR WAY STOPS
IF THEY ARE UNSTAFFED AND GET OUT OF THE WAY OF EMERGENCY
VEHICLES WHEN NECESSARY. WE ALSO NEED TO KNOW THAT THE
DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT, THE FIRE DEPARTMENT
AND THE MUNICIPAL TRANSPORT TRANSPORTATION AGENCY ARE
CONFIDENT IN THE RESPONSIVENESS OF BOTH WAYMO AS A COMPANY
AND INDIVIDUAL WAYMO VEHICLES TO MOVE OFF THE STREETS DURING
EMERGENCIES. >> THAT IS WHY I'M CALLING FOR
A HEARING TO BE HELD IN THE COMING WEEKS ON WAYMO'S
RESPONSE TO THE DECEMBER POWER OUTAGES AND ENSURING THAT CITY
AGENCIES HAVE THE TOOLS NECESSARY TO DEAL WITH THESE
NEW ENTRANTS TO THE TRANSPORTATION SYSTEM IN TIMES
OF EMERGENCY. >> I'M INVITING WAYMO
LEADERSHIP TO ANSWER QUESTIONS ABOUT THE POINTS OF FAILURE FOR
THEIR VEHICLES AND WHAT THEY ARE DOING TO IMPROVE OPERATIONS
MOVING FORWARD. >> I'M ALSO INVITING TEAM AS
THE FIRE DEPARTMENT AND MTA TO DISCUSS HOW WE CAN AVOID WHAT
EXPERIENCED LAST MONTH FROM HAPPENING AGAIN.
THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR WANG AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR YOUR
CO-SPONSORSHIP OF THIS HEARING AND YOUR COLLABORATION
AND PROACTIVITY ON OUR CITY'S RESPONSE TO THIS UNACCEPTABLE
INCIDENT. >> THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I WILL
SUBMIT MY LEGISLATION AND LET'S GO TO GENERAL MR. PRESIDENT.
>> SUPERVISOR WALTON HAS TO BE REFERRED RIGHT AS WELL.
THANK YOU, PRESIDENT BENJAMIN. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES WITH DEEP RESPECT AND GRATITUDE I WANT TO READ
THIS IN MEMORIAM AND HONOR THE LIFE AND LEGACY OF MY TIE.
CHIEF SATOSHI TO RITA TO SAY MOSHE TAGA.
A DEVOTED PUBLIC SERVANT COMMUNITY LEADER AND BELOVED
FAMILY MAN MR. C A TIGER DEDICATED 33 YEARS OF SERVICE
TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO INCLUDING 19 YEARS AS
A MUNI BUS OPERATOR. THROUGH HIS STEADY PRESENCE
AND UNWAVERING COMMITMENT HE PLAYED A VITAL ROLE IN KEEPING
SAN FRANCISCO MOVING AND ASSURING THE SAFETY,
RELIABILITY AND DIGNITY OF PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION FOR
COUNTLESS RESIDENTS AND VISITORS.
HIS WORK REFLECTED NOT ONLY PROFESSIONALISM BUT ALSO CARE
FOR THE PEOPLE HE SERVED EVERY DAY.
BEYOND HIS CAREER, MR. CITY TIGER WAS DEEPLY COMMITTED TO
COMMUNITY FROM EARLY ON. HE WAS INVOLVED WITH THE SAMOA
MOST SAMOA NONPROFIT ORGANIZATION WHERE HE WORKED TO
UPLIFT SAMOAN AND PACIFIC ISLANDER FAMILIES, PRESERVE
CULTURAL TRADITIONS AND STRENGTHEN
INTERGENERATIONAL CONNECTIONS. AS A MIGHTY CHIEF HE EMBODIED
LEADERSHIP ROOTED IN SERVICE, HUMILITY AND COLLECTIVE
RESPONSIBILITY. BORN IN SAMOA IN THE VILLAGE OF
TUG TARGUM MINDANAO, MR. A CARRIED HIS CULTURAL VALUES
WITH THE PRIDE WITH PRIDE THROUGHOUT HIS LIFE.
>> HIS LEGACY IS ONE OF HARD WORK COMPASSION, FAITH
AND DEDICATION TO BOTH FAMILY AND COMMUNITY.
>> MR. C A TIGER PASSED AWAY ON DECEMBER 22ND, 2025.
HE IS SURVIVED BY HIS LOVING WIFE URSULA NOWICKI A TIGER.
12 CHILDREN, EIGHT GRANDCHILDREN AND THOUSANDS OF
NIECES AND NEPHEWS ALL OF WHOM CARRY FORWARD HIS SPIRIT,
TEACHINGS AND LOVE. >> WE EXTEND OUR DEEPEST
CONDOLENCES TO HIS FAMILY AND ALL WHO WERE TOUCHED BY HIS
LIFE. HIS CONTRIBUTIONS TO SAN
FRANCISCO AND TO THE SAMOAN AND PACIFIC ISLANDER COMMUNITY
WILL NOT BE FORGOTTEN. REST IN PEACE CHIEF.
YOUR SERVICE AND LEGACY LIVE ON THE REST AS A THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR WALTON. >> MR. PRESIDENT, LET'S GET TO
PUBLIC COMMENT. AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES
YOUR GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT. IF YOU WOULDN'T MIND LINE UP TO
YOUR RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER ALONG THE CURTAINS.
>> YOU MAY SPEAK TO THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED EARLIER.
ITEMS 14 AND 15 ON THE ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE
AGENDA AND OTHER GENERAL MATTERS THAT ARE NOT ON TODAY'S
AGENDA BUT MUST BE WITHIN THE BOARD'S SUBJECT MATTER
JURISDICTION. AND WE'RE SETTING THE TIMER FOR
TWO MINUTES. AND WELCOME TO THE FIRST
SPEAKER. >> HI, HOW ARE YOU?
MY NAME IS MOLLY. I'M A HOMEOWNER IN DISTRICT
FOUR. EXCUSE ME, MOLLY, CAN YOU SPEAK
DIRECTLY INTO THAT MICROPHONE? THANK YOU.
MY NAME IS MOLLY. I'M A HOMEOWNER IN DISTRICT
FOUR. AND I HAVE THREE KIDS AND A
HUSBAND AND A CAT DOG AND A LIZARD.
>> I'M PART OF A GROUP CALLED OUTER MAMAS.
WE'RE 800 STRONG AND I LIVE I LEAD A POLITICAL SUBCOMMITTEE
CALLED SUNSET PARENT ADVOCATES. AND I WANT TO TALK ABOUT
SOMETHING THAT WASN'T ADDRESSED TODAY WAS EXTREMELY TIMELY
WHICH IS SUNSET DUNES. >> IT'S INTERESTING TO SEE
TODAY THAT WE'RE HONORING STEWARDSHIP OF OUR PARKS
BECAUSE I THINK IT'S WELL KNOWN THAT YOU ALL AND MR. WONG WOULD
LIKE TO INTRODUCE A BALLOT TO REOPEN THE GREAT HIGHWAY
AND CLOSE DOWN SUNSET DUNES. >> I JUST WANT TO SPEAK FOR MY
FAMILY AND THE FAMILIES. I KNOW WE USE IT EVERY SINGLE
DAY AND WE DON'T WANT TO COMPROMISE AS THAT ENABLES IT
TO ONLY BE OPEN ON THE WEEKENDS AND CARS DURING THE WEEK THAT
EFFECTIVELY DESTROYS AND IT TAKES AWAY OUR PUBLIC PLACE
STRUCTURES, OUR ART, OUR SKATE RAMPS.
IT TAKES AWAY THE WIND PHONE WHICH I PERSONALLY FIND VERY
SACRED BECAUSE I TALK TO MY DAD AND MY GRANDPARENTS AND MY
COUSIN AND MY AUNT WHO ALL LEFT ME IN THE PAST FEW YEARS AND I
THINK IT'S A SACRED SPACE TO A LOT OF OTHER PEOPLE.
>> AND SO I ASK YOU TO PLEASE NOT DESTROY THE PLACE WHERE WE
CONNECT TO OUR PAST AND CONNECT TO OUR FAMILIES PRESENTLY
BECAUSE YOU'RE LISTENING TO PEOPLE WHO MAY WANT TO LIVE
IN THE PAST AND I GET IT PEOPLE ARE ANGRY THAT THE ROAD CLOSED
AND THEY'RE LOUD BUT I THINK THEY'VE MOVED ON.
>> THEY'VE FOUND OTHER ROUTINES.
AND I ASK YOU TO PLEASE LISTEN TO THE FAMILIES WHO ARE TOO
BUSY TO COME HERE TODAY BECAUSE WE HAVE KIDS IN SCHOOL DROP
OFFS AND BABIES AND AGING PARENTS.
>> BUT WE'RE OUT THERE EVERY DAY.
WE'RE THERE AT 10 P.M. WHEN MY BABY CAN'T SLEEP AND WE'RE
THERE AT 6 A.M. WHEN THE TODDLER WAKES UP TOO EARLY.
AND IT'S BECAUSE WE'RE THERE ALL THE TIME THAT IT'S THE
THIRD MOST POPULAR PARK IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THE PEOPLE OF THE CITY VOTED.
THE GOVERNOR SAID IT WAS A LEGACY.
THE NEW YORK TIMES SAID THAT OTHER CITIES SHOULD FOLLOW OUR
EXAMPLE AND YOU CAN EVEN CONSIDER SORRY.
>> THANK YOU, MOLLY THAT THAT CONCLUDES YOUR TIME.
IF YOU HAVE SOMETHING TO HAND IN, WE'RE HAPPY TO TAKE THAT
FROM YOU, MOLLY WE'RE HAPPY TO TAKE IT FROM YOU AND WE'LL PUT
IT INTO THE MINUTES, OKAY? ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU KINDLY. >> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER, PLEASE. YEAH.
ARTHUR GOOD AFTERNOON, CHAIRMAN COLEMAN AND MEMBERS OF THE
BOARD. MY NAME IS SARAH YULE AND I'M
WITH PG ANNIE'S GOVERNMENT AFFAIRS ON DECEMBER 20TH A
PIECE OF EQUIPMENT AT OUR MISSION STOP STATION FAILED
WHICH RESULT? WHICH RESULTED IN A FIRE
AND APPROXIMATELY 130,000 CUSTOMERS LOSING POWER.
>> SINCE THAT TIME THERE HAVE BEEN POCKETS OF CUSTOMERS
IN THE RICHMOND AND THE SUNSET DISTRICTS THAT HAVE EXPERIENCED
ADDITIONAL OUTAGES AND WE ARE ADDRESSING THE CAUSE OF THESE
OUTAGES TO IMPROVE OUR CUSTOMER EXPERIENCE.
WE HAVE HIRED AN INDEPENDENT INVESTIGATOR COMPANY NAMED
EXPONENT TO CONDUCT A ROOT CAUSE INVESTIGATION.
WE ARE PUSHING TO HAVE THIS INVESTIGATION COMPLETED AS SOON
AS POSSIBLE AND WILL LIKELY HAVE PRELIMINARY RESULTS
IN FEBRUARY WHICH WE WILL SHARE WITH THE CITY.
WE ARE EAGER TO PARTICIPATE IN THE HEARING THAT HAS BEEN
REQUESTED AND ANY OTHER AFTER ACTION MEETINGS THAT WILL HELP
US IMPROVE COORDINATION IN THE FUTURE AS A CAUSE OF THE
EQUIPMENT FAILURE IS STILL UNKNOWN.
WE RESPECTFULLY ASK THE BOARD TO REFRAIN FROM DRAWING ANY
CONCLUSION UNTIL THE INVESTIGATION RESULTS ARE
AVAILABLE. WE WOULD ALSO ASK THAT YOU WAIT
TO SCHEDULE THE HEARING UNTIL AFTER THE PRELIMINARY RESULTS
OF THE EXPONENT REPORT ARE RELEASED IN FEBRUARY.
SO THAT THE HEARING IS WELL INFORMED AND MOST PRODUCTIVE.
WE'RE GOING TO BE TRANSPARENT WITH OUR LEARNINGS AND ARE
COMMITTED TO MAKING ANY RECOMMENDED IMPROVEMENTS WITH A
SENSE OF URGENCY. >> WE ARE PROUD OF OUR ONGOING
INVESTMENTS TO ENHANCE THE SYSTEM THAT SERVES SAN
FRANCISCO. WE ARE CONTINUING TO MAKE
ADDITIONAL INVESTMENTS AND WE REMAIN COMMITTED TO WORKING
CLOSELY WITH THE CITY TO LEARN FROM THIS OUTAGE AS WE
STRENGTHEN RESILIENCE AND BUILD A FUTURE READY UTILITY.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> AND GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT
MANAGEMENT AND BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS RICHARD STEVE PETERSON ORDINARY LEE I TALK
ABOUT PARCEL TAXES AND THE EFFECT OF PARCEL TAXES ON THE
WEST SIDE VERSUS PARCEL TAXES AND THE DOWNTOWN REGION.
BUT I THE MAYOR'S PLAN FOR TRANSIT IS UNDER THREAT.
I KNOW THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS HAS TAKEN CERTAIN STEPS TO
AMELIORATE THE POTENTIAL EFFECTS OF THE TRANSIT PLAN I
100% SUPPORT MUNI I TAKE MUNI I DON'T DRIVE SO THAT'S OUT OF
THE QUESTION. BUT WHAT I WOULD LIKE TO WARN
YOU ABOUT IS THE NEW BILL SB 677 IT IS BEING PROPOSED BY THE
UP I. REPRESENTATIVE ACTUALLY FROM
SAN FRANCISCO REGARDING DEVELOPMENT AND THE POTENTIAL
EFFECT IT WILL HAVE ON SPECULATION ON ALL OF THE
HOUSING AND ALL OF THE DEVELOPMENT THAT THE MAYOR IS
PLANNING AND THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IS ATTEMPTING TO
CONTROL. SO IN ANY EVENT KEEP YOUR EYES
OUT FOR SB 677. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
MY NAME IS ZACH SHARP AND I WORK FOR LUMINOUS SOLAR A WOMAN
OWNED SOLAR AND LOCAL SOLAR INSTALLER THAT HAS BEEN IN SAN
FRANCISCO FOR 22 YEARS. AS SUPERVISOR CHAN DORSEY
AND WONG ALREADY BROUGHT UP AS SAN FRANCISCO WAS HIT WITH A
RECENTLY HIT WITH A MASSIVE POWER OUTAGE THAT LEFT OUR
RESIDENTS COLD IN THE DARK AND SCARED BECAUSE THEIR HOME
SECURITY SYSTEMS AND HEALTH CARE EQUIPMENT LIKE VENTILATORS
WEREN'T WEREN'T WORKING. >> OUR RESIDENTS WEREN'T JUST
INCONVENIENCED THEY WERE LESS SAFE.
HUNDREDS OF ALUMINUM CLIENTS, HOWEVER, ONLY EXPERIENCED THAT
OUTAGE FOR A FRACTION OF A SECOND AS THEIR SOLAR
AND BATTERY SYSTEMS INSTANTLY WENT INTO BACKUP MODE AND BEGAN
POWERING THEIR HOUSES. >> WHILE THIS SOLUTION SO
OBVIOUSLY BENEFITS SAN FRANCISCANS SAN FRAN SOLAR
AND STORAGE HAS BEEN FACING IMMENSE HEADWINDS FROM EVERY
LEVEL OF GOVERNMENT OBVIOUSLY FROM THE FEDERAL AND STATE BUT
WE ARE GETTING HIT HARDEST HERE AT HOME IN SAN FRANCISCO.
LOCAL SAN FRANCISCO FIRE CODE HAS BEEN MAKE HAS MADE
INSTALLING BATTERIES SO OVERLY COMPLEX AND COSTLY THAT SAN
FRANCISCO HAS THE REPUTATION FOR BEING THE MOST DIFFICULT
PLACE TO INSTALL HOME STORAGE BATTERIES IN THE COUNTRY.
AND IF YOU DON'T BELIEVE ME JUST ASK CHAT GBP WE FULLY
UNDERSTAND THAT THE FIRE DEPARTMENT TAKES EXTREMELY
CONSERVATIVE APPROACH WHEN DETERMINING THEIR
INTERPRETATIONS OF FIRE CODE WITH THE GOAL OF SAFETY AND WE
AGREE THAT SAFETY IS THE MOST IMPORTANT GOAL FULL STOP.
THAT IS WHY WE DON'T THINK THAT LIMITING WHO CAN MAKE THEIR
HOME SAFE AND RESILIENT TO ONLY THE WEALTHIEST IN OUR CITY IS
GOOD POLICY TO JUST GIVE IT ONE EXAMPLE SOLAR AND SOLAR
INSTALLATIONS ONLY NEED ONE INVERTER.
HOWEVER, IF A HOME REQUIRES MULTIPLE BATTERIES, MULTIPLE
INVERTERS ARE REQUIRED WHICH INCREASES COSTS BY THOUSANDS OF
THOUSANDS OF DOLLARS AND PROVIDES NO ADDITIONAL
SAFETY. WE UNDERSTAND THAT THE 2025
FIRE CODE WILL BE GIVEN TO YOU IN THE NEXT WEEK OR SO.
WE ASK THAT YOU KEEP SAFETY AND RESILIENCE RESILIENCE YOU
HAVE OUR RESIDENTS IN MIND AS YOU REVIEW IT.
THERE ARE OTHER PLANNED INTERPRETATIONS OF FIRE CODE
THAT WILL CONTINUE TO STRANGLE SOLAR AND STORAGE LIKE
REQUIRING THREE FOOT CLEARANCE AROUND ALL SKYLIGHTS.
>> SO AT A TIME THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS OR IF YOU'D LIKE
TO SUBMIT THAT FOR THE RECORD WE'RE HAPPY TO TAKE THAT FROM
YOU. >> ALL RIGHT.
BEFORE WE HEAR FROM THE NEXT SPEAKER, IF THERE ARE ANY OTHER
SPEAKERS IN THE AUDIENCE WHO'D LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD
DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT, NOW'S YOUR TIME TO GET IN LINE.
>> WELCOME, SIR OR MEMBERS OF SAN FRANCISCO AND MAYOR OFFICE
OF SAN FRANCISCO. THE FOLLOWING MESSAGE HAS
BACKING FROM ELON MUSK, MARK ZUCKERBERG, BILL GATES
AND JASON WAN, CEO OF NVIDIA IS TITLE TO TCP GENERATE
GENERATION TWO TRANSMISSION PROTOCOL.
AS I MENTIONED IN MY PREVIOUS PUBLIC COMMENT I'M GOING TO 48
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES. I KNOW IT'S GOING TO BE A HARD
PILL TO SWALLOW FOR A LOT OF PEOPLE IF AND IF CHIEF
EXECUTIVE I'M GOING TO DO IT RIGHT FROM THE GET GO.
WHEN I WAS A KID MY MOM WHO PASSED AWAY IN 2012 FORCED ME
SIGN ME UP FOR AFTERSCHOOL CHINESE PROGRAM.
I LOST INTEREST AND EVENTUALLY DROPPED OUT AND THAT'S MY
CHINESE NAME. WHEN YOU GROW UP YOU REGRET IT
. AND SHE IS RIGHT.
SINCE MY COLLEGE YEARS I STARTED TO LEARN CANTONESE BUT
I CANNOT READ CANTONESE. I CAN ONLY MEMORIZE IT
PHONETICALLY. HOW SO?
AND TO WHAT? JOHNSON WHAT WAS IT TELLING
YOUR STORY? >> SHE ONCE MET A JAPANESE
GARDENER PICKING TINY LITTLE MOSS IN A LARGE GARDEN AND SHE
APPROACHED HIM AND SAID WHY ARE YOU PICKING THESE TINY MOSS?
AND IT WAS SO BIG. AND WHAT HE SAID IS I HAVE ALL
THE TIME IN THE WORLD. SO BASICALLY WHEN YOU DO
SOMETHING THAT YOU LOVE, YOU HAVE ALL THE TIME IN THE WORLD
JUST BEFORE THE END OF 2025 I SUBMITTED A MESSAGE TO THE
MAYOR OF SAN CISCO AND TACKLED THE $600 MILLION BUDGET
DEFICIT. HOW I TO DO THAT?
I COME AND REPORT VERY SLOWLY WEEK BY WEEK AND TELL YOU ALL
THIS BACKING FOR THE TECH EXECUTIVE HOUSING A START TO
GENERATION TO TRANSMISSION PROTOCOL WHICH PAYS WASTE FOR
FLYING CARS FOR NEXT CENTURY. IF YOU LOOK UP TO INTERNET THE
TIMES MAGAZINE IT SAYS ARCHITECT OF SETI YOU KNOW MOST
RECENTLY I SAID HE SAYS BACKING ON ME AS A CHIEF ARCHITECT OF A
HIGH TECH THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME, MR. DUFFY MY NAME'S DUFFY.
I'M A RESIDENT OF THE TENDERLOIN.
THE LESS POLITICAL NAME OF THE AREA IS THE NORTH OF MARKET
PLANNING AREA. IT'S ACTUALLY IN MOST OF IT'S
IN DISTRICT FIVE BUT THERE ARE ACTUALLY TWO PARTS OF IT THAT
ARE IN DISTRICT THREE AND DISTRICT SIX BUT I JUST
MAKE A GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT THAT IF SOMEONE COMES UP HERE
AND ASKS YOU TO VERIFY SOMETHING BY ASKING CHAD GPT
THREE YOU SHOULD TAKE THAT FOR WHAT IT'S WORTH.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. ARE THERE ANY OTHER SPEAKERS
IN THE CHAMBER? >> WELCOME.
GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS AND PRESIDENT MANDOLIN.
I'M KAT ANDERSON, PRESIDENT OF THE PARK COMMISSION.
I'M HERE TO SPEAK ON ITEM 14. IN THE NAME OF FUN THERE'S AN
OPPORTUNITY TO COMMEMORATE COMMEMORATIVE LEE NAME A STREET
IN GOLDEN GATE PARK AFTER OUR BELOVED ALLIGATOR CLOD.
AND I JUST WANTED TO SAY A COUPLE OF THINGS ABOUT CLAUDE.
I WAS PARTICULARLY SADDENED BY CLAUDE'S PASSING BECAUSE CLAUDE
WAS HATCHED IN 1995 THE SAME YEAR MY SON PATRICK AND HE IS
DEVOID OF PIGMENT PIGMENT MUCH LIKE MY VERY WHITE SON PATRICK
WHO WOULD BE COMPLETELY MORTIFIED IF HE KNEW I WAS HERE
SAYING IT TODAY AND HE ALSO CAME TO THE CALIFORNIA ACADEMY
OF SCIENCES CLAUDE DID IN 2008 ALONG WITH MY FAVORITE
PRESIDENT OBAMA. >> BUT WE'RE GOING TO HAVE A
GREAT TIME. I BELIEVE THERE'S GOING TO BE A
COMMUNITY CELEBRATION JANUARY 28TH WHICH WE'LL PROBABLY HEAR
ABOUT MORE FROM SUPERVISOR MELGAR AND JUST WANTED TO SAY
THAT YOU DO A LOT OF HARD STUFF AND YOU HANDLE A LOT OF TOUGH
PROBLEMS BUT IT IS FUN TO DO THINGS JUST FOR THE HECK OF IT.
>> SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT. ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED. MADAM CLERK.
LET'S GO TO OUR FOR ADOPTION OF THAT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA
ITEMS 14 AND 15 ITEMS 14 THROUGH 15 WERE INTRODUCED FOR
ADOPTION BUT WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS
REQUIRED FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING
TODAY. ALTERNATIVELY, A MEMBER MAY
REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST APPEARANCE TO GO TO COMMITTEE
SUPERVISOR MELGAR 14 PLEASE THAT'S SEVEN ITEM 14 AND MADAM
CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 15 ON ITEM 15
SUPERVISOR MELGAR I MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SORTER I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WILSON EYES
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I THEN SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN ALL
RIGHT RANDLEMAN I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 14 ITEM
14 RESOLUTION TO URGE THE RECREATION AND PARK COMMISSION
TO COMMEMORATIVE LEE NAME A STREET IN GOLDEN GATE PARK
CLAUDE THE ALLIGATOR WAY SUPERVISOR MELGAR, THANK YOU SO
MUCH AND THANK YOU COLLEAGUES FOR HEARING THIS ITEM AT FIRST
I WANT TO THANK YOU KNOW OUR ILLUSTRIOUS PRESIDENT OF THE
REC PARK COMMISSION, KAT ANDERSON FOR BEING HERE AND FOR
THE PARTNERSHIP WITH THE DEPARTMENT AND THE ACADEMY OF
SCIENCES. AS YOU PROBABLY KNOW, WE
ENTERED INTO A PARTNERSHIP WITH MISSION LOCAL TO ASK SAN
FRANCISCANS ABOUT HOW WE SHOULD RENAME THE STREET IN THE PARK
AFTER CLAUDE WE GOT AN OUTPOURING OF JUST WONDERFUL
INVOLVEMENT FROM SAN FRANCISCANS.
THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE VOTED VOTED ON THIS.
I THINK SOME OF YOU DID TOO. >> BUT WHAT STRUCK ME THE MOST
IS WE ALSO GOT SO MANY LIKE EMAILS, TEXT MESSAGES, PHONE
CALLS FROM PEOPLE WHO TOLD US WONDERFUL STORIES OF THEIR
MEMORIES WITH CLAUDE OF HOW IMPORTANT HE WAS TO THEIR
CHILDHOOD TO GROWING UP TO FINALLY FINDING ABOUT THE
NATURAL WORLD, TO INTERACTING WITH OUR PARKS AND THE ACADEMY
OF SCIENCES. IT REALLY REPRESENTED THE BEST
OF WHO WE ARE AS A CITY AND HOW WE TAKE UP THAT RESPONSIBILITY
OF STEWARDSHIP OF NATURE AND TAKING CARE OF OTHERS
WHETHER THEIR OWN SPECIES OR OTHER SPECIES.
FOLKS KNOW THAT CLAUDE WAS A LITTLE BIT DIFFERENT THAT
IN THE WILD HE PROBABLY WOULD NOT HAVE SURVIVED TO THE LONG
AGE THAT HE LIVED IN IN AT THE ACADEMY OF SCIENCES.
SO AGAIN I'M REALLY GRATEFUL. THANK YOU FOR YOUR SUPPORT THIS
IS THE THIRD TIME THAT WE DO THIS AT THE DISTRICT SEVEN
OFFICE AFTER VOTING ON BLUE HERON LAKE AND ALSO ON THE
PARENTS AND THAT WAS GREAT FUN. IT'S A GREAT WAY TO INVOLVE THE
CITIZENS OF SAN FRANCISCO IN SOMETHING THAT WE ALL WILL
REMEMBER AND THAT YOU KNOW, MARKS AN IMPORTANT PLACE IN OUR
CITY AND IN OUR HEARTS. SO I ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT FOR
THIS RESOLUTION. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. ROSENBERGER I THINK WE CAN TAKE
THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED AND MADAM
CLERK, DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS?
>> THERE ARE NONE TO REPORT. >> MR. PRESIDENT, COULD YOU
PLEASE READ THE IN MEMORIAM YESTERDAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS
ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR CHERYL FOR THE LATE MR. DIOSDADO PALM
MITTEN BINOTTO ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR WALTON FOR THE LATE
MATAI CHIEF SATOSHI TAVETA SIMO KITAGAWA AND I BELIEVE THAT
BRINGS US TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE
ANY FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY?
>> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR TODAY THEN WE ARE ADJOURNED